{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "According to legend, Horatio Nelson’s body was stored in this substance after the Battle of\nTrafalgar. This product was created as a way to dispose of the molasses created as a byproduct of\nthe manufacture of sugar in the Caribbean. In the British Navy, Edward Vernon created the\npractice of diluting this substance with water. For 10 points, name this component of grog.",
      "answer": "rum"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What Russian tsar freed the serfs in 1861 and was assassinated twenty years later?",
      "answer": "Alexander II"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader forcibly dismissed the Rump Parliament and replaced it with Barebone’s\nparliament. He was hated in Ireland for atrocities committed at Wexford and Drogheda. He\nhelped win the Battle of Naseby as a cavalry commander in the New Model Army. For 10 points,\nname this man who served as Lord Protector of England in the interregnum following the\nexecution of Charles I of England.",
      "answer": [
        "Oliver Cromwell",
        "Cromwell"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Nobility serving under this dynasty followed the \"Table of Ranks\" to determine bureaucratic\nadvancement. This royal house came to power after three different \"False Dmitris\" were\nsuppressed during the Time of Troubles. For 10 points, name this house founded by Mikhail I in\n1613, which remained in control of Russia until the twentieth century.",
      "answer": [
        "Romanov",
        "Romanov Dynasty"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This king ordered the destruction of all remaining Protestant churches in the Edict of\nFontainebleau (pr. FAHN-tohn-blow). He was opposed at his accession by the Fronde\nmovement, which was countered by his early advisor, Cardinal Mazarin. For 10 points, name this\nmonarch who reigned for seventy-two years as the absolutist \"Sun King\" of France.",
      "answer": "Louis XIV"
    },
    {
      "question": "This party was victimized by the Zinoviev letter hoax, which purported to show Soviet control\nof its operations and brought down its first prime minister, Ramsay Macdonald. This party was\nfirst represented in Parliament by Scottish coal miner Keir Hardie. For 10 points, name this\nparty, now the more left-wing of the two largest political parties in the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": [
        "Labour Party",
        "Labour"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the autumn of 1649, this man led armies which sacked Drogheda (pr. DRAH-huh-dah),\nleading to his reputation as a cruel conqueror of Ireland. He was succeeded by his son Richard\nafter his death. For 10 points, name this leader of the New Model Army who attained supreme\npower as \"Lord Protector of England\" after the Civil War.",
      "answer": [
        "Oliver Cromwell",
        "Cromwell"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS EXAMPLE) What President of Germany, who appointed Hitler Chancellor in 1933, was the\nnamesake of a zeppelin that caught fire above New Jersey in 1937?",
      "answer": [
        "Paul von Hindenburg",
        "Hindenburg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the end of this decade, the Mayerling scandal erupted. During this decade, Chinese Gordon\nwas killed fighting the Mahdi in Sudan. The rules for colonialism were set out at the Berlin\nConference during this decade. For 10 points, identify this decade in which Queen Victoria\ncelebrated the Golden Jubilee of her 1837 accession to the throne.",
      "answer": [
        "1880s"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What city defeated Genoa (in the Chioggia (pr. kee-OH-juh) War and grew into a great\nmaritime power under the leadership of \"doges?\"",
      "answer": "Venice"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the nineteenth century, this country experienced the Liberal Triennium. An attempt to\nenforce the Salic Law in this country sparked the first Carlist War. This country lost nearly all of\nits overseas colonies during the early nineteenth century following the rise of Jose de San Martin\nand Miguel Hidalgo. For 10 points, name this onetime master of much of Latin America.",
      "answer": "Spain"
    },
    {
      "question": "This modern-day country was outraged by the Council of Blood being imposed as its ruler, as\nwell as by the Tenth Penny tax. It allied with the \"Sea Beggars\" against Spanish governors such\nas the Duke of Alba and won its independence in the Eighty Years War. For 10 points, name this\ncountry where William the Silent reigned over land reclaimed from the sea via dikes.",
      "answer": [
        "the Netherlands",
        "Holland",
        "the United Provinces"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman was implicated in a fraud known as the Affair of the Diamond Necklace. She\nbecame known as \"the widow Capet\" following the death of her husband, Louis XVI. For 10\npoints, name this queen of France who legendarily dismissed a crowd of peasants crying out for\nbread by saying \"let them eat cake.\"",
      "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
    },
    {
      "question": "This military leader was declared a martyr by Pope Callixtus III, a generation after this saint's\ncapture at Compiègne (pr. cahmp-YEN-yuh). Pierre Cauchon (pr. COO-shun) led the court\nwhich condemned her to be burned at the stake in 1431 following her relief of the siege of\nOrléans (pr. OH-lee-ahn). For 10 points, name this teenage French patriot of the Hundred Years\nWar.",
      "answer": [
        "Joan of Arc",
        "Jeanne d'Arc"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The \"July Theses\" defined the Communist regime of what Eastern European country,\nwhose Ploiești (pr. ploy-ESH-tuh) oil fields were targeted by Operation Tidal Wave?",
      "answer": "Romania"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person was appointed as the head of an expedition to Scutari (pr. scoo-TAH-ree) by\nwar minister Sidney Herbert, who knew of her efforts to improve sanitation. She became known\nas the \"Lady with the Lamp\" for her efforts during the Crimean War. For 10 points, name this\n1850s British woman, the founder of modern nursing.",
      "answer": [
        "Florence Nightingale",
        "Nightingale"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When it became apparent that this event had failed, a disgusted Erich Ludendorff simply\nwalked away, leading its main organizer to be sentenced to the Landsberg, where Mein Kampf\nwas written. For 10 points, name this failed 1923 attempt by Adolf Hitler to seize power in\nGermany by leading an uprising at a Munich drinking venue.",
      "answer": "Beer Hall Putsch"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man said he planned to use a Kärcher pressure-washer to \"clean out\" suburbs. In 2014,\nthis former leader of the UMP was questioned by police for alleged corruption in a judicial\nappointment in Monaco. He lost a close re-election bid in 2012 to his left-wing rival François\nHollande (pr. frah-SWAH oh-LAHND). For 10 points, name this former President of France.",
      "answer": [
        "Nicolas Sarkozy",
        "Sarkozy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The \"condottiere\" (pr. cahn-DOE-tee-AIR-ee) were what type of soldiers, who fought\nmost of the wars of Renaissance Italy and were often of English origin and whose use was\nwarned against by Machiavelli?",
      "answer": "mercenaries"
    },
    {
      "question": "The process of creating these places was paused after the article \"Dizzy From Success.\" The\nattempt to bring the entire countryside into these places resulted in the Holodomor and other\nepisodes of famine, as well as direct killings of alleged \"kulaks.\" For 10 points, the First Five Year Plan was aimed at transforming all Soviet agriculture into what socialist institutions?",
      "answer": [
        "Soviet collective farms",
        "collective farms",
        "sovkhoz",
        "kolkhoz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A powerful advisor based in this city uncovered the Tavora (tuh-VORE-uh) Conspiracy. This\ncity, where the Marquis of Pombal came to power, was the location of a 1755 disaster that\ninspired philosophers across Europe to ask how God could allow large-scale death. For 10\npoints, name this city that was devastated by a large earthquake described in Candide.",
      "answer": "Lisbon"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ship never fought a major battle, as it was under upgrades during Jutland (YUT-land).\nThis ship was designed at the behest of First Sea Lord Jacky Fisher and targeted in a namesake\n\"hoax\" by Virginia Woolf, who pretended to be an Ethiopian princess. For 10 points, name this\nship whose construction spurred a battleship \"arms race\" in the decade before World War I.",
      "answer": [
        "HMS Dreadnought",
        "Dreadnought"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, the preacher John Ball posed the riddle “When Adam delve and Eve span,\nwho was then the gentleman?” This event ended shortly after William Walworth, the mayor of\nLondon, beheaded its leader. This event targeted Richard II and protested the 1380 poll tax. For\n10 points, name this 1381 uprising in England led by Wat Tyler among a class of people.",
      "answer": "the Peasants' Revolt"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Todor Zhivkov was the longtime Communist dictator of what Eastern European\ncountry, which used ricin pellets fired out of a modified umbrella to assassinate dissidents, and\nroughly corresponds to ancient Thrace?",
      "answer": "Bulgaria"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man advocated for a “priesthood of all believers” in the work To the Christian Nobility of the\nGerman Nation. He was protected by Frederick the Wise after Charles V ordered his arrest. Pope Leo X\nexcommunicated this man with the bull Exsurge Domine [EX-ur-gay DOE-mee-nay] after he posted the\n95 Theses. For ten points, name this German priest who began the Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": [
        "Martin Luther",
        "Luther"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler attempted to establish the Kingdom of Livonia as a vassal state, and this ruler established\nhis country’s first printing press at Kitai-gorod. This ruler conquered Kazan and Astrakhan, and he\nestablished a secret police force known as the Oprichniki. Feodor I succeeded this ruler after he killed his\neldest son in a fit of rage, eventually leading to the Time of Troubles. For ten points, name this first Tsar\nof Russia whose epithet notes his power, not his cruelty.",
      "answer": [
        "Ivan IV of Russia",
        "Ivan IV",
        "Ivan the Terrible",
        "Ivan Grozny"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The War of Jenkins’ Ear was part of what larger conflict over succession to a European\nthrone?",
      "answer": [
        "War of the Austrian Succession",
        "Austrian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This family’s crest pictures a red cow eating grass against a yellow background. One member of this\nfamily hosted an orgy in the Banquet of the Chestnuts. That man, the enemy of Girolamo Savonarola,\nhad formed the League of Venice to oppose Charles VIII’s invasion of Italy. That man’s son had embarked\non the Romagna campaign, and was the inspiration for Niccolo Machiavelli’s The Prince. For ten points,\nname this Italian family whose members included Cesare and Pope Alexander VI.",
      "answer": [
        "Borgia family",
        "Borgia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The aftermath of this event led to the creation of the Quadruple Alliance and the formation of the 38\nstate German Confederation. It restored the Bourbon Dynasty in France with Louis XVIII. This meeting\nwas interrupted by the Hundred Days and it was headed by Austrian minister Klemens von Metternich.\nFor ten points, name this 1815 meeting that sought to organize post-Napoleonic Europe.",
      "answer": "Congress of Vienna"
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman defeated the Emirate of Granada, ending the Reconquista period of her country. She\nsponsored the trips of an explorer from Genoa who started Spanish colonization of the New World. For\nten points, name this Castilian queen who married Ferdinand II of Aragon and sponsored the trips of\nChristopher Columbus.",
      "answer": [
        "Isabella I of Castille",
        "Isabella"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gave the Appeal of 18 June Speech during one war. This leader’s opposition to the European\nCommission led to the Empty Chair Crisis. He was later criticized after Expo 67 for proclaiming “Long\nlive free Quebec!” This man’s government ended a conflict with the FLN by signing the Evian Accords.\nHe was brought to power in the May Crisis, leading to the formation of the Fifth Republic. For ten points,\nname this French Prime Minister who led the Free French Forces during WWII.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles de Gaulle",
        "Gaulle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this battle, Major Sylvain-Raynal managed to defend Fort Vaux for over a week, but the lightly\ndefended Fort Douaumont [DOO-oh-MOHN] was captured without a fight. General Nivelle issued the\norder “they shall not pass” during this battle, and General Falkenhyn sought to “bleed France white”\nin this battle. For ten points, name this extremely bloody 9-month-long battle during World War I at a\nFrench fortress town.",
      "answer": "Verdun"
    },
    {
      "question": "One side’s attack on Saarbrucken early in this war showed the value of their Chassepot [sha-say-poh]\nrifles, but was defeated at the Battle of Wissembourg [VISS-em-boorg]. The Army of Chalons was formed\nduring this war to rescue troops encircled at Metz, and this war was ended by the Treaty of Frankfurt.\nThe Second Empire was dissolved after a defeat at Sedan in this war. For ten points, name this war that\nresulted in the formation of the German Empire and the defeat of Napoleon III.",
      "answer": [
        "Franco-Prussian War",
        "Franco-Prussian",
        "Franco-German War",
        "Franco-German",
        "War of 1870"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "King Godfred built the Danevirke as a defense against this ruler, and later this ruler concluded the\nTreaty of Heiligen with the Hemming. This ruler, who died of pleurisy, was succeeded by his son Louis the\nPious, and three of his grandsons divided his empire in the Treaty of Verdun. This ruler, who was advised\nby Alcuin of York, was crowned on Christmas Day by Leo III as Imperator Romanorum. For ten points,\nname this King of the Franks who was the first Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Charlemagne",
        "Charles I",
        "Carolus Magnus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This author wrote about a drunk Pope Julius II who tries to convince Julius into letting him into\nheaven in Julius Exclusus, and he advocated for Christians to act with faith in his Handbook of a Christian\nKnight. Hans Holbein created drawings for this man’s best known work, which satirizes the workings of\nthe Catholic Clergy. For ten points, name this Dutch humanist who wrote In Praise of Folly.",
      "answer": [
        "Desiderius Erasmus",
        "Erasmus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A war against the town of Visby led to a conflict between this country and the Hanseatic League.\nChristian I was the first member of this country’s Oldenburg dynasty, the oldest continuously reigning\ndynasty in Europe. This nation was briefly ascendant over Sweden and Norway in the Kalmar Union and\nis currently ruled by Frederik X. For ten points, name this country with capital at Copenhagen.",
      "answer": "Denmark"
    },
    {
      "question": "An attempt to implicate Jews for one of this man’s actions involved an apron located just below the\nGoulston Street graffito; that apron belonged to Catherine Eddows. That event proved that this man’s\n“Dear Boss” letter wasn’t a hoax. Later, this man mailed a kidney to George Lusk with his “From Hell”\nLetter. For ten points, name this officially unidentified serial killer of London’s Whitechapel district.",
      "answer": "Jack the Ripper"
    },
    {
      "question": "A photo by Yevgeny Khaldei [khal-DAY] shows a soldier raising a flag atop a building in this city. In\nthis city, the mural My God, Help Me to Survive This Deadly Love depicts Leonid Brezhnev and Erich\nHonecker embracing. Lucius D. Clay led relief during Operation Vittles which was known as this city’s\n“Airlift”. For ten points, name this capital of Germany",
      "answer": "Berlin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader bribed journalists with the Reptile Fund. His education minister, Adalbert Falk,\nadministered the May Laws, and he called a conference to modify the Treaty of San Stefano. He also\ncalled another conference of the same name, which incited the Scramble for Africa. This man sent the Ems\ndispatch to spark war against France, which resulted in his forming a unified country under the Prussian\nmonarch Wilhelm I. For ten points, name this Chancellor who unified Germany.",
      "answer": [
        "Otto von Bismarck",
        "Bismarck"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Warning: two answers required. These two countries planned, but never took, a joint voyage to map\na boundary defined as 370 leagues west of Cape Verde. These two countries debated ownership of the\nIndonesian Molucca Islands until the 1529 Treaty of Zaragoza, 35 years after they divided New World\nterritory in the Treaty of Tordesillas [torr-de-SEE-ess]. For ten points, name these two countries on the\nIberian peninsula in southwestern Europe.",
      "answer": [
        "Spain and Portugal",
        "Castille and Portugal"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This monarch employed Chancellor John Morton and defeated a rebellion at the Battle of Stoke;\nthat rebellion was led by pretender Lambert Simnel. This monarch, who established the Star Chamber,\ndefeated a Yorkist king with the help of the Stanley brothers at one battle.This man defeated the forces\nof Richard III at the Battle of Bosworth Field, ending the Wars of the Roses. For ten points, name this\nfirst Tudor monarch and father of Henry VIII.",
      "answer": "Henry VII"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The execution of what victor of the Battle of Stirling Bridge seemed to end the Scottish\nWar of Independence, prior to the rise of Robert the Bruce?",
      "answer": [
        "William Wallace",
        "Wallace"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This event’s fourth principle declared that “superior orders” do not relieve a person from lawful\nresponsibility. Seven subjects of these events were taken to Spandau. Their location was chosen\nsymbolically, as it had hosted an annual propaganda rally and was the city where, in 1935, a harsh set of\nanti-Semitic laws was signed. Luftwaffe commander Hermann Goring was sentenced to death at, for ten\npoints, what series of trials in which Nazi leaders were tried for war crimes?",
      "answer": [
        "Nuremberg trials",
        "Nuremberg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this modern day country, Boleslaw [boll-eh-slav] the Pious of this country’s Piast Dynasty\ngranted Jews legal rights with the Statue of Kalisz [kal-eesh]. In this modern day country, the Szaltcha\n[SHALL-chah] enacted the Golden Liberty under its Jagiellion [yah-gell-ee-on] dynasty. This modern day\ncountry has been partitioned between Russia, Prussia, and Austria. For ten points, name this eastern\nEuropean nation with capital Warsaw.",
      "answer": "Poland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler faced early trouble from two Eberhards, of Bavaria and Franconia, and his half-brother\nThankmar during his early reign. Liudolf, this man’s son, fought against him before a notable battle, and\nJohn XII crowned this man before being deposed by this ruler. This son of Henry the Fowler was aided by\nConrad the Red to defeat the Magyars at the Battle of Lechfeld. For ten points, name this Saxon German\nking, the first Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Otto I",
        "Otto the Great",
        "Otto"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What man became France’s first Socialist president in 1981?",
      "answer": [
        "Francois Mitterand",
        "Mitterand"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader appointed Ian MacGregor as head of the National Coal Board, which closed unprofitable\nmines, angering Arthur Scargill. This leader narrowly won a vote of no confidence to depose James\nCallaghan, and was succeeded by John Major after a cabinet minister resigned due to her combative style.\nThis Prime Minister formed a friendship with Ronald Reagan and won the Falklands War. For ten points,\nname this Iron Lady, the first female Prime Minister of the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": [
        "Margaret Thatcher",
        "Thatcher"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After a war with the Ottomans, this empire annexed Bessarabia and supported the founding of\nindependent Bulgaria. This empire annexed Khiva and Bukhara during the “Great Game” with the\nUnited Kingdom. In 1825, a succession crisis in this empire led to the Decembrist uprising of soldiers who\nsupported Grand Duke Constantine, who instead remained in Poland. For ten points, name this empire\nthat, in the 19th century, was led by three Alexanders from the Romanov family.",
      "answer": [
        "Russian Empire",
        "Russia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man consolidated his power when his rival Harry von Arnim was caught pilfering secret\ngovernment records. This leader provoked a war in which his nation gained Alsace-Lorraine after the\nbattles of Sedan and Metz. Leo von Caprivi succeeded this editor of the Ems Dispatch, who espoused the\npolicy of realpolitik [real-pol-ih-teek] in the “Blood and Iron” speech. For ten points, name this instigator\nof the Franco-Prussian War, an “Iron Chancellor” credited with unifying the German states.",
      "answer": [
        "Otto von Bismarck",
        "Bismarck"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Sultanate of Rum failed to stop this campaign, in part because the Danishmends had tied up the\nforces of Alp Arslan. Peter the Hermit inspired the poor to aid this campaign, whose participants rallied\naround the the cry “Deus vult!” Following the Battle of Manzikert, Alexius Comnemnus was forced to\nrequest this campaign to counteract the power of the Seljuk Turks. Pope Urban II’s Council of Clermont\nbegan, for ten points, what Christian campaign that retook Jerusalem from the Muslims in 1099?",
      "answer": "First Crusade"
    },
    {
      "question": "This war’s French theater included a victory for the Duc d’Enghien [”duke” don-GYEN] at the Battle\nof Rocroi [roh-CWAH]. The Bohemian phase of this war ended with the Battle of White Mountain and\nthe defeat of the Winter King. Wallenstein and the Count of Tilly served as Imperial generals during this\nwar, in which Gustavus Adolphus was killed. The Peace of Westphalia ended, for ten points, what war\nfought over religion in modern-day Germany that lasted from 1618 to 1648?",
      "answer": [
        "Thirty Years’ War",
        "Thirty Years"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler resolved territorial disputes with Nader Shah by signing the Treaty of Resht and failed to\nform an alliance with William III. This man employed Patrick Gordon to capture Azov, which he later\ngave back to Ahmed III. He gave civil service a structured hierarchy via the Table of Ranks as part of an\neffort to reform the bureaucracy, and he disbanded the streltsy. The boyars lost both political power and\ntheir beards under the reign of, for ten points, what “Great” modernizing tsar of Russia?",
      "answer": [
        "Peter the Great",
        "Peter I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man exiled a rival to Compiegne after she tried to have this man dismissed in the Day\nof the Dupes. This rival of Marie de Medici and founder of the Academie Francaise engineered the siege of La Rochelle and French participation in the Thirty Years’ War, and was known as the “Red Eminence”. For ten points, name this cardinal and chief minister to Louis XIII.",
      "answer": [
        "Cardinal Richelieu",
        "Richelieu",
        "Armand Jean du Plessis",
        "du Plessis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Soldiers attacking this capital city during Operation Danube were deceived into thinking they were\noperating against fascist elements. In protest of human rights abuses, Jan Palach set himself on fire in\nthis city’s Wenceslas Square. A meeting in this city led to the the removal of Antonin Novotny as First\nSecretary and the ascension of Alexander Dubcek [doob-check], who began a series of liberalizing reforms.\nFor ten points, identify this namesake of a 1968 “Spring” uprising against Communism, the capital of\nCzechoslovakia.",
      "answer": "Prague"
    },
    {
      "question": "A replica of this structure in Alliance, Nebraska was made from cars spray-painted grey. Early\nconstruction at this site included a round ditch and pits known as Aubrey holes. The material for this\nstructure may have been quarried in Marlborough Downs or Wales. The sarsen trilithons that make up\nthe outer ring of this structure were built using mortise and tenon joints, and they align with the sun\nduring the summer and winter solstice. For ten points, name this Neolithic structure on Salisbury Plain\nin Southern England.",
      "answer": "Stonehenge"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man competed with Christopher Columbus’ unhappy son as the governor of Puerto Rico. In\n1521, this man was mortally wounded in a skirmish with the Caloosahatchee by a poisoned arrow; his\nmen sailed him to Havana, where he died. For ten points, name this Spanish explorer, the first European\nto set foot in the modern United States, whose 16th century travels in Florida did not find the Fountain\nof Youth.",
      "answer": [
        "Juan Ponce de Leon",
        "Ponce de Leon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man is in the center of a mosaic in the Basilica of San Vitale in Ravenna, which was conquered\nby the man to his right in that mosaic. The first appearance of Yersinia pestis in Europe occurred during\na plague named for this man. Belisarius conquered the Vandals for this ruler, whose reign was described\nin Procopius’s Secret History. The Nika Riots opposed this husband of Theodora. For ten points, name\nthis Byzantine emperor who published a law code in 529 AD.",
      "answer": [
        "Justinian I",
        "Justinian",
        "Justinian the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What Soviet foreign minister negotiated a non-aggression pact with Joachim von\nRibbentrop and is the namesake of an anti-tank “cocktail” created by Finnish soldiers?",
      "answer": [
        "Vyacheslav Mikhailovich Molotov",
        "Molotov",
        "Molotov cocktail"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After this city soundly defeated an opposing fleet at Curzola, the opposing admiral, Andrea Dandolo,\ncommitted suicide. This city’s fleet was led by Luciano and Pietro Doria during the War of Chioggia,\nwhich it lost, marking the end of its rivalry with Venice. This Ligurian city’s fleet was led at the Battle of\nLepanto by Andrea Doria. For ten points, name this city on the northwest coast of Italy, the birthplace of\nexplorer Christopher Columbus.",
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Genoa",
        "Genoa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler annexed Bavaria from Tassilo III and conquered Saxony from Widukind, massacring\nthousands of Saxons at Verden. He divorced his wife Desiderata in 771, then conquered her homeland of\nLombardy. This ruler, who established his capital at Aachen, is the subject of an Einhard biography. This\nson of Pepin the Short restored Leo III to Rome, who crowned him on Christmas Day 800. For ten points,\nname this King of the Franks and first Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Charlemagne",
        "Karl der Grosse",
        "Carolus Magnus",
        "Charles the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During one of these campaigns, a king died with his son John Tristan, who had been born in Damietta\nduring a different one of these campaigns. The leader of one of these campaigns, Simon de Montfort, was\nkilled while besieging Toulouse. The Albigensian one of these conflicts defeated the Cathars in the south\nof France, and Louis IX was canonized for his efforts in the seventh and eighth ones of these against Egypt\nand Tunisia. For ten points, name these conflicts, called by the Pope, that targeted religious enemies.",
      "answer": "crusades"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s wife, Katharina von Bora, was forced to evacuate the Black Cloister during the\nSchmalkaldic War. This man received the protection of Frederick III of Saxony and debated Zwingli in\nthe Marburg Colloquy. This critic of Johann Tetzel was excommunicated at the Diet of Worms after\nprotesting the sale of indulgences on the door of Wittenberg Cathedral. For ten points, name this German\nmonk whose Ninety-Five Theses started the Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": [
        "Martin Luther",
        "Luther"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man killed the Sheriff of Lanark, William Heselrig, at Lanark. Blind Harry chronicled the life\nof this man, an ally of Andrew Moray. John de Menteith captured this man, who was hung, drawn, and\nquartered in 1305. This subject of John Balliol was defeated at Falkirk, inspiring Robert the Bruce to\ntake up his cause. For ten points, name this opponent of Edward Longshanks and winner at the Battle of\nStirling Bridge, a hero of Scottish independence.",
      "answer": [
        "William Wallace",
        "Wallace"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What Russian city on the Baltic Sea was the site of a 900 day siege by Nazi forces during\nWorld War II?",
      "answer": [
        "Leningrad",
        "Saint Petersburg",
        "Petrograd"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One side in this battle used the Pitomnik airfield to supply bomber raids on the Red October factory\nand Barrikady tractor works. Erwin Konig was supposedly killed at this battle in a duel against rival\nsniper Vasily Zaitsev. This battle turned when Erich von Manstein failed to counter Operation Uranus,\nleaving Friedrich Paulus’ 6th Army entrapped by Georgi Zhukov’s Soviet troops. For ten points, name\nthis 1942-43 battle of the Eastern Front fought for a Russian city on the Volga River",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Stalingrad",
        "Stalingrad"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Anif Document ended centuries of Wittelsbach rule in this state. Prussia and Austria fought\nover this state in a war of succession known as the Potato War. This state, which fought with Napoleonic\nFrance against its eastern neighbor, Austria, was once ruled by Ludwig the Mad, who built the castle\nof Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-shtein]. For ten points, name this primarily Catholic state in southern\nGermany whose capital is Munich.",
      "answer": [
        "Bavaria",
        "Bayern"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During his first Parliament, this man confiscated all the land holdings of his predecessor’s wife,\nElizabeth Woodville. Shortly after this man became king, the children Richard of Shrewsbury and\nEdward V mysteriously disappeared after being taken to the Tower of London. This man’s remains had\ndisappeared for centuries until, in 2012, they were found under a parking lot. For ten points, name this\nsubject of a Shakespeare history, the final king of the House of York.",
      "answer": "Richard III"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) During World War II, Vidkun Quisling led a collaborationist regime in what country,\nwhose people now use “Quisling” as a synonym for traitor?",
      "answer": "Norway"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1858, this object was recast in Whitechapel, after which a team spent 18 hours hauling this\nobject to its belfry. This object was silenced following the death of Margaret Thatcher, and is currently\ndisconnected during renovations of Elizabeth Tower. “Quarter bells” that play the Westminster Chimes\nevery 15 minutes accompany, for ten points, what massive bell that names an iconic London clock tower?",
      "answer": [
        "Big Ben",
        "bell in Big Ben"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, heavy fighting took place near Papelotte and La Haye Sainte. Michel Ney led a\nfailed cavalry charge against the British during this battle, where the British Foot guards repelled an\nattack by the French Imperial Guard, their first defeat. The arrival of the Prussian army under Blucher\nswung the tide in, for ten points, what 1815 victory for the Duke of Wellington, the last major battle of\nthe Napoleonic Wars?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Waterloo",
        "Waterloo"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Two weeks before this battle, the invading force made their landing at Pevensey. During this battle,\none side’s housecarls made a stand on Senlac Hill until their leader was struck in the eye by an arrow.\nThis battle arose out of a dispute over whom Edward the Confessor named as his successor. The Bayeux\nTapestry depicts the death of Harold Godwinson in, for ten points, what battle that confirmed William\nthe Conqueror’s rule over England in 1066?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Hastings",
        "Hastings"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, Walter Ulbricht initially denied building what later became known as the Anti-Fascist\nProtection Rampart. In 1963, JFK claimed that it was the “proudest boast” of a free person to be a\ncitizen of this city. Later, Ronald Reagan spoke in front of this city’s Brandenburg Gate and commanded\nGorbachev to tear down this city’s wall. For ten points, name this once-divided city whose eastern half\nserved as the capital of East Germany.",
      "answer": "Berlin"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was enflamed when a court-martial acquitted Ferdinand Esterhazy. One person\ninvolved in this scandal was imprisoned on Devil’s Island until key evidence against him was\nrevealed to be forged. Emile Zola wrote the letter J’Accuse supporting that prisoner. For 10\npoints, name this scandal in which a Jewish French army captain was framed for treason.",
        "answer": [
          "Dreyfus affair",
          "Dreyfus"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another 19th century French political scandal concerned Ferdinand de Lesseps’\nattempts to build what structure?",
        "answer": "Panama Canal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire followed the proclamation of the Edict of Gulhane with a fifty year modernization\neffort called the Tanzimat Reforms. Some of its armies were composed of irregular “bashibazouks,” while others were composed of janissaries. It was known as the Sick Man of Europe\nleading up to World War I. For 10 points, name this empire which centered on Turkey.",
        "answer": [
          "Ottoman Empire",
          "Ottoman"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first president of modern Turkey was what man who implemented a namesake\npolicy of strict westernization?",
        "answer": [
          "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
          "Ataturk"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man first came to prominence by suppressing the 13 Vendémiaire (pr. VON-deem-yair)\nrebellion with what Thomas Carlyle called \"a whiff of grapeshot.\" He made his brothers Joseph\nand Jerome into the kings of Spain and Westphalia, respectively. For 10 points, name this \"First\nCounsel\" who was defeated by the Duke of Wellington at Waterloo.",
        "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte, Napoleon, Napoleon I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Napoleon was able to remove Austria and the Holy Roman Empire from the Third\nCoalition opposing him with what great 1805 victory in what is now the Czech Republic?",
        "answer": "Austerlitz, Battle of Austerlitz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A scandal leading up to this ballot question involved abusive Twitter messages sent to J.K.\nRowling. Alistair Darling appeared in an August 2014 debate on behalf of Better Together,\nwhich led the \"no\" campaign on this question. For 10 points, identify this September 2014 ballot\nquestion which sought to make Edinburgh the capital of a new sovereign country.",
        "answer": "Scottish independence, Scottish independence referendum"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which largest Scottish city by population was one of the few areas where the majority\nof people voted for independence?",
        "answer": "Glasgow"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Troops who carried out this action referred to it as “Blumenkrieg”, a term meaning \"war of\nflowers,\" because they were met by cheering crowds. Kurt Schuschnigg (pr. SHOOS-neg) was\nforced to resign to clear the way for this action, which began on March 11, 1938. For 10 points,\nidentify this forced incorporation of Austria into Nazi Germany.",
        "answer": "Anschluss"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Austria was forbidden from unifying with Germany by the Treaty of Saint-Germain\n(pr. sahn zhair-MON), which was signed at the end of what war?",
        "answer": "World War I, First World War, the Great War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A bronze age museum is maintained at a \"crannog\" in County Clare on this island. This island\nregained its independence from Viking kingdoms at the 1014 Battle of Clontarf, re-establishing\nthe High King's seat at the hill of Tara. The Book of Kells can be seen at Trinity College Library\non this island. For 10 points, name this island, also home to the James Joyce Museum in Dublin.",
        "answer": "Ireland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What city in southwest Ireland is the namesake of a humorous poetic form?",
        "answer": "Limerick"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s government organized the Congress of People’s Deputies and signed the\nIntermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty. He introduced economic restructuring known as\n\"perestroika\" (pr. peh-rez-TROY-kuh) and government transparency called \"glasnost\". For 10\npoints, name this rival of Boris Yeltsin who was the final leader of the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": [
          "Mikhail Gorbachev",
          "Gorbachev",
          "Mikhail Sergeyevich Gorbachev"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gorbachev ended the \"internal exile\" of what dissenting physicist, the inventor of the\nSoviet hydrogen bomb and namesake of a human rights prize?",
        "answer": [
          "Andrei Sakharov",
          "Sakharov",
          "Andrei Dmitrievich Sakharov"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The U.S. National Archives currently displays David Rubenstein’s copy of this document,\nwhich contains clauses that limited the right of women to use the legal system and limited the\nenforcement of debts against children. This document was signed at Runnymede and failed to\nquell the Barons Wars. For 10 points, name this limitation of the powers of King John.",
        "answer": "Magna Carta"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Second Barons War ended under the rule of what king, whose army was defeated\nby William Wallace at Stirling Bridge?",
        "answer": [
          "Edward I",
          "Edward Longshanks",
          "Longshanks"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was targeted by the Unilateral Declaration of Independence, which removed a\ncolony from this empire to protest its plans for racial integration. This empire's leader gave the\nWinds of Change speech as it began to give up control of Ghana, Nigeria, and Rhodesia. For 10\npoints, name this empire which, along with France, was the largest colonizer of Africa.",
        "answer": [
          "British Empire",
          "British",
          "UK",
          "United Kingdom",
          "Great Britain",
          "Britain"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rhodesia later was renamed as which African country with its capital at the city of\nHarare (pr. huh-RAH-ray)?",
        "answer": "Zimbabwe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This device was originally named for doctor Antoine Louis. The \"tricoteuse\" (pr. TRICK-awtooz) were women who knitted next to this object. This object was used on up to forty thousand\npeople at the order of Maximilien Robespierre, who found himself subject to it in 1794. For 10\npoints, name this item which was used to execute Louis XVI and others during the French\nRevolution.",
        "answer": "guillotine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The guillotine was originally used to equalize execution methods for nobles and\nmembers of what group, the peasant section of France in the Estates-General?",
        "answer": [
          "Third Estate",
          "Third"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Popes from this family presided over the Council of Trent and the start of the Protestant\nReformation. This family of Leo X and Pius IV was targeted by the Pazzi (pr. POT-see)\nConspiracy and first rose to power in Tuscany under the banker Cosimo. For 10 points, identify\nthis political family which ruled Florence through such members as Lorenzo the Magnificent.",
        "answer": [
          "de Medici",
          "Medici"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What rival family of Spanish origin included Pope Alexander VI, the poisoner\nLucrezia, and the Machiavelli (pr. MOCK-ee-uh-VEL-ee) patron Cesare (pr. CHAY-zar-ay)?",
        "answer": "Borgias"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The informer \"Stakeknife\" infiltrated this organization, which began the \"Long War\" in the\nearly 1970s. This group claimed responsibility for killing MP Airey Neave as well as the 1984\nBrighton hotel bombing which nearly killed Margaret Thatcher. For 10 points, name this militant\nCatholic group which advocated transferring Northern Ireland away from the United Kingdom.",
        "answer": [
          "IRA",
          "Irish Republican Army",
          "Provisional IRA",
          "Provisional Irish Republican Army"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which 1972 massacre of Irish demonstrators by UK paratroopers shares its name with\na 1905 killing spree in St. Petersburg?",
        "answer": "Bloody Sunday"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This queen came to the throne at age six, leading to the creation of a regency council\ndominated by Axel Oxenstierna (pr. OCK-sens-TURR-nuh). In 1654, this queen shocked\nEurope by abdicating her throne and converting to Catholicism, after which she lived out her life\nin Rome. For 10 points, name this daughter of Gustavus Adolphus, an “enlightened monarch” of\nSweden.",
        "answer": [
          "Queen Christina",
          "Christina"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Christina’s energetic studies with what philosopher of Discourse on Method, whom she\nsummoned to Sweden and often woke before dawn, are thought to have caused his death?",
        "answer": "Rene Descartes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Eighth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution copied nearly verbatim this text’s prohibition\non “excessive bail and cruel and unusual punishments.” This document guaranteed freedom of\nspeech and the right to bear arms, and it also banned Catholics from succeeding to the throne.\nFor 10 points, name this 1689 law which outlined liberties prior to the Glorious Revolution.",
        "answer": [
          "English Bill of Rights",
          "Bill of Rights"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What editor of The North Briton whose slogan was “No Liberty, No King” caused\nrepeated scandals in 1760s England by invoking the English Bill of Rights in his campaign\nagainst George III?",
        "answer": [
          "John Wilkes",
          "Wilkes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A picket line formed by members of this profession got into a huge brawl with police at the\nBattle of Ogreave. Members of this profession who opposed the moderate NACODS joined the\nNUM led by Arthur Scargill. Members of this profession were dubbed \"the enemy within\" by\nMargaret Thatcher. For the point, identify this profession which launched a disastrous 1984\nBritish strike which closed down facilities for extracting bitumen.",
        "answer": [
          "coal miners"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which musical about a boy who wants to be a ballet dancer features a chorus of\ndisgruntled coal miners complaining about Margaret Thatcher?",
        "answer": "Billy Elliott"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The inefficient Trabant was built in this former country. It used distinctive Ampelmannchen crosswalk\nsymbols that are now enjoyed as its modern residents experience “Ostalgie.” Its residents were once spied\non by the Markus Wolf-led Stasi, which revealed its records after reunification in 1990. For ten points,\nname this former Soviet-zone country with capital Berlin.",
        "answer": [
          "East Germany",
          "German Democratic Republic",
          "GDR",
          "Deutsche Demokratische Republik",
          "DDR"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Oder-Neisse Line provided the border between East Germany and what other country?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Poland",
          "Poland"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man fought during the Second Baron’s War against Simon de Montfort, who he killed at the\nBattle of Evesham. This monarch issued the Edict of Expulsion, which expelled all Jews from England.\nHe invaded Scotland, winning the Battle of Falkirk against the forces of William Wallace. For ten points,\nname this English King given the name “Longshanks” because of his height.",
        "answer": "Edward I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Edward I’s father Henry III was forced by the barons to agree to the Provisions of Oxford, which\nheavily influenced this later document that was signed by John I at Runnymede.",
        "answer": "Magna Carta"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This position was ended by the Peace of Pressburg, which also created the Confederation of the\nRhine. One holder of this position stood in the snow outside Canossa to do penance, and the successor to\nthis position was decided by the prince-electors. These men were crowned by popes until 1530, and the\nphrase “sacrum” was added to this title by a man who fought the Lombard League. For ten points, name\nthis position, which was held by Charles V and Frederick Barbarossa.",
        "answer": [
          "Holy Roman Emperor",
          "Romisch-deutscher Kaiser",
          "Romanorum Imperator"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 1356 decree known by this color was issued by Charles IV to set the number of electors to\nselect the Holy Roman Emperor at seven.",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Bull of 1356",
          "Gold",
          "Bulla Aurea"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alcuin of York’s letters lament these people’s sacking of a priory on the Northumbrian island of\nLindisfarne. The Great Heathen Army legendarily avenged the death of one of their leaders, Ragnar\nLodbrok. Leif Erikson founded their colony of Vinland in the New World. For ten points, name these\nScandinavian sea-faring raiders whose longships dominated medieval Europe for four centuries.",
        "answer": "Vikings"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "True to his name, this legendary discoverer of Greenland was Leif Erikson’s father.",
        "answer": [
          "Eric the Red",
          "Eric Thorvaldsson"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “liquidators” dealt with the aftermath of this event, which was detected after a day in Forsmark,\nSweden. The Red Forest was created by this event, which led to a “zone of alienation” being marked\naround the city of Pripyat. It was triggered by a poorly-safeguarded experiment in which control rods\nwere manually removed, spreading radiation over much of Europe. For ten points, name this 1986 nuclear\nmeltdown in modern Ukraine.",
        "answer": [
          "Chernobyl nuclear disaster",
          "Chernobyl"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Chernobyl disaster was a major catalyst towards this Soviet premier’s adoption of glasnost,\na policy of openness and government transparency.",
        "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Mitchel was sent to Bermuda as punishment for his writings about this event. During this event,\npeople called “soupers” converted to Protestantism in return for aid. The cottier system worsened this\nevent, in which the affected area received shipments of maize known as “Peel’s brimstone” and remained\na net food exporter to Britain. For ten points, over a million people starved in what event in which the\nstaple crop of an island west of Britain was ruined by blight?",
        "answer": [
          "Irish Potato Famine",
          "Great Famine",
          "Great Hunger"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In response to the Irish Potato Famine, Prime Minister Robert Peel repealed what set of tariffs\non imported grain in 1846?",
        "answer": "Corn Laws"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person’s childhood friend, the Princess de Lamballe, was murdered in the September Massacres.\nThe Carnation Plot attempted to save this monarch, a suspected lover of Axel Fersin. This monarch was\nwrongly blamed in the Diamond Necklace affair and was derisively called “the Austrian”. For ten points,\nname this Queen of France, who may have said “let them eat cake” and was guillotined after her husband\nLouis XVI.",
        "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Axel Fersin helped plan the escape of Marie Antoinette and Louis XVI from France, but they\nwere recognized at this small town near the border between Montmedy and Saint-Menehould.",
        "answer": "Varennes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler ignited a rebellion after appointing Yuri Dolgoruki to round up fugitive peasants in lands\nled by Kondraty Bulavin. This ruler signed the Treaty of Constantinople with Mustafa II, which led to\nthis ruler creating his country’s first navy base on the Sea of Azov. He instituted a beard tax for the\nboyars and traveled incognito to observe a Dutch shipyard as part of his Grand Embassy. For ten points,\nname this “great” Czar whose modernization included the founding of Saint Petersburg.",
        "answer": [
          "Peter I",
          "Peter the Great"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Peter I was a part of this Russian Dynasty which ruled Russia until the fall of Nicholas II.",
        "answer": [
          "Romanov dynasty",
          "Romanov"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This year saw the National Liberal party push Frederick VII to create a new constitution, which made\nhim share power with the Rigsdag. This year saw William O’Brien lead the Young Irelander Rebellion,\nand the March Revolution in this year in Germany led to the Frankfurt Assembly offering the German\ncrown to Wilhelm IV. Klemens von Metternich resigned as Chancellor of Austria in this year, which\nsaw the establishment of the French Second Republic. For ten points, name this year that saw multiple\nrevolutions against various European Governments.",
        "answer": "1848"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wilhelm IV was from this royal line that would rule Imperial Germany until the end of WW1.",
        "answer": [
          "Hohenzollern Dynasty",
          "Hohenzollern"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This party lost an election to Stanley Baldwin due to the Zinoviev Letter. This party’s 1983 election\nmanifesto was called by one man as the “longest suicide note in history”. James Callaghan of this\nparty suffered the Winter of Discontent which saw the rise of the opposition party’s leader Margaret\nThatcher. For ten points, name this British political party formerly led by Ed Milliband which opposes\nthe Conservatives and Liberals.",
        "answer": [
          "United Kingdom Labour Party",
          "Labour"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ed Milliband was replaced by this self-described democratic socialist as leader of the Labour\nParty after an abysmal showing in the UK 2015 elections. This MP from Islington North was originally\nconsidered a fringe candidate.",
        "answer": [
          "Jeremy Corbyn",
          "Corbyn"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man built a fort on Aethelney Hill while hiding out in the Somerset marshes. Bishop Asser relates\nhow this man was once scolded by an old woman for letting a bunch of cakes burn, and he baptized one\nrival as his godson; he defeated that rival at the battle of Eddington. This victor of the Battle of Ashdown\nfortified his country with a system of burhs. For ten points, name this ruler, the enemy of Guthrum of\nMercia and king of Wessex, who was known as “the Great.”",
        "answer": [
          "Alfred the Great",
          "Alfred"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alfred succeeded the first King of this name as leader of Wessex. The second English leader of\nthis name earned the epithet “the Unready” for the poor counsel of his advisors.",
        "answer": "Aethelred"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Flight of the Wild Geese refers to one group of these people who left Ireland. Machiavelli praised\none type of them, although he considers them as useless as auxiliaries. Leaders of these in Italy were called\ncondottieri [con-doh-tee-AIR-ee], and the battle of Marignano saw the ascendancy of the Landsknecht\nover the most famous of these types of soldiers, who were recruited from their cantons and carried pikes.\nSwiss pikemen were, for ten points, what hired soldiers?",
        "answer": "mercenary"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Swiss mercenaries were most commonly hired by what nation, whose Francis I employed them\nat the battles of Marignano and Pavia?",
        "answer": "France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alexander Suvorov invaded this country through the St. Gotthard Pass during the French\nRevolutionary wars. The Toggenburg War was fought by the Old Confederacy of this country, which\nwas formed from Uri, Schwyz, and Unterwalden. The Kappel wars were fought in this country, where\nNapoléon established the Helvetic Republic. Zürich is one of eight Old Cantons in, for ten points, what\nAlpine country that has its capital at Bern?",
        "answer": "Switzerland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This author of Institutes of the Christian Religion and supporter of predestination fled to\nSwitzerland and eventually led the church of Geneva.",
        "answer": [
          "John Calvin",
          "Calvin"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This king wrote the Defence of the Seven Sacraments attacking Martin Luther, for which he was\nrewarded with the title Defender of the Faith from Clement VII. This man, who passed the first Act\nof Supremacy and dissolved the monasteries, ordered his chief ministers Cardinal Wolsey and Thomas\nCromwell to arrange an annulment and marriage to Anne Boleyn. For ten points, name this King who\nfounded the Church of England so that he could divorce the first of his six wives.",
        "answer": [
          "Henry VIII Tudor",
          "Henry VIII"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry’s first, fifth, and sixth wives had this name. The first was a relative of Ferdinand and\nIsabella of Spain, the fifth was executed after sixteen months for adultery, and the last survived by\noutliving Henry.",
        "answer": "Catherine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was forced to retreat through the Derbend Pass after his invasion of Sassanid Persia. This\nman’s uncle Ruga united his people, then was succeeded by this man and his brother, Bleda. Aetius was\nforced to ally with Theodoric in order to defeat this ruler, who may have begun an invasion after Honoria\nsent him a ring. According to legend, this ruler died of a nosebleed. For ten points, name this “Scourge of\nGod” who attempted to sack Rome as the leader of the Huns.",
        "answer": [
          "Attila",
          "Attila the Hun"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Upon invading Italy, Attila was confronted by Leo I, a holder of this religious position, outside Rome.",
        "answer": "Pope"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, murderous mitrailleuse [mih-tray-uhs] and Chassepot [shass-poh] fire stalled one\nside’s attacks at the Battle of Gravelotte. After this war, Baden, Wurtemburg, and Bavaria joined a\ncountry that also gained Alsace-Lorraine through the Treaty of Frankfurt. This war ended shortly after\nthe losing leader was captured at the Battle of Sedan. For ten points, name this war in which Napoleon\nIII was soundly defeated by a state led by Otto von Bismarck.",
        "answer": [
          "Franco-Prussian War",
          "Franco-Prussian"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prussia was the first country to adopt the use of this material for making artillery, which helped\nit win the Franco-Prussian War. Krupp guns are made of this material.",
        "answer": "steel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Third Section was one of these organizations before it was succeeded by the Okhrana. Before\nhe held his highest post, Yuri Andropov was the head of one of these organizations. One of these\norganizations, the oprichniki, targeted the boyars and executed the Massacre of Novgorod. A feared one of\nthese during the Cold War was known as the Committee for State Security, or the KGB. For ten points,\nname these organizations that suppressed dissent in Russia.",
        "answer": [
          "Russian secret police",
          "secret police",
          "intelligence agencies",
          "intelligence"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Yuri Andropov’s tenure as head of the KGB, he advocated for the Soviet Union’s 1979\ninvasion of this country, often described as the USSR’s “Vietnam.”",
        "answer": [
          "Democratic Republic of Afghanistan",
          "Afghanistan"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was able to lift trading restrictions after signing the Treaty of Kucuk Kaynarca [koo-chook\nkai-nar-ka]. This ruler descended from the royal family of Anhalt and founded the Hermitage. Cossacks\ntargeted this patron of Voltaire during Pugachev’s Rebellion. Fake villages to show prosperity were\nconstructed by this ruler’s lover, Grigory Potemkin. For ten points, name this enlightened despot and\n18th century Empress of Russia.",
        "answer": [
          "Catherine the Great",
          "Catherine II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Catherine the Great collaborated with Prussia and Austria in the first of three partitions of this\ncountry. This country would not become independent again until after World War I.",
        "answer": [
          "Poland-Lithuania",
          "Poland"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Marco Antonio Bragadin was flayed alive after surrendering Famagusta in the name of this city. This\ncity’s Arsenale [ar-seh-NAH-lay] was said to be able to produce a warship a day, helping it repel multiple\nOttoman invasions of Corfu. This city ruled over Crete after its leader, Enrico Dandolo, sacked Zara and\nagreed to provide transportation for the Fourth Crusade. For ten points, name this Queen city of the\nAdriatic, an Italian city known for its many canals.",
        "answer": [
          "Most Serene Republic of Venice",
          "Venice"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Enrico Dandolo was one of numerous Venetian rulers with this title, derived from the word for\nduke. These people were elected by 41 members of the Great Council.",
        "answer": [
          "Doge",
          "Doxe"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s ruler was greatly embarrassed by the revelation of Philipp zu Eulenburg’s [oy-len-burg’s]\nhomosexuality. This country sent a gunboat to its rival’s territory in Morocco, causing the Agadir Crisis.\nIts high command was led by Helmuth von Moltke, and it was accused of sending the Zimmerman\nTelegram, causing the United States to declare war on this country. Kaisers led, for ten points, what\nmember of the Central Powers, an empire that invaded France during World War I?",
        "answer": [
          "Germany",
          "German Empire",
          "Second Reich",
          "Kaiserreich"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The early 20th century German empire held a naval arms race with the UK, consisting primarily\nof building these “all big gun” steam battleships. This class of ship was named for a British vessel.",
        "answer": "dreadnoughts"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Protestants and Catholics in this country fought the Kappel Wars. The Helvetic Republic was briefly\nimposed on this country, whose cantons were formally united into one country in 1848. Unterwalden,\nSchwyz [shveetz], and Uri formed the Old Confederation of this modern country, whose other cantons\ninclude Lucerne and Zurich. For ten points, name this Alpine country, which has its capital at Bern.",
        "answer": "Switzerland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Swiss pikemen often served as this type of soldier in the service of other European powers. Other\nEuropean examples of these unaffiliated soldiers for hire include Landsknechts and condottieri.",
        "answer": "mercenary"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This war began with a failed invasion of the Danubian Principalities. One side in this war built the\nGreat Redan and a Malakoff redoubt to defend the city of Sevastopol. This war’s Battle of Balaclava\nincluded the heroism of the Thin Red Line and the disastrous Charge of the Light Brigade. Florence\nNightingale served as a medic in, for ten points, what war fought between by an Anglo-French alliance\nover a Russian peninsula in the Black Sea?",
        "answer": [
          "Crimean War",
          "Crimean"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Charge of the Light Brigade was an attempt to attack a formation of these weapons. The\nBritish captured a set of these weapons at Sevastopol, which were legendarily melted down for the steel\nused to make Victoria Cross medals.",
        "answer": [
          "cannons",
          "artillery"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was succeeded in one of his territories by Robert Curthose and required all landowners to\npledge their loyalty via the Salisbury Oath. This ruler conducted the Harrying of the North and landed\nat Pevensey to begin an invasion. The compilation of the Domesday Book [”Doomsday Book”] survey\nwas ordered by this leader, who defeated a king who had just won the Battle of Stamford Bridge. For ten\npoints, name this leader who became King of England after winning the Battle of Hastings.",
        "answer": [
          "William the Conqueror",
          "William I of England",
          "William I",
          "William II of Normandy",
          "William the Bastard"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "William the Conqueror defeated this man at the Battle of Hastings. He had previously defeated\nHarald Hardrada, king of Norway, who was also trying to claim the throne.",
        "answer": [
          "Harold Godwinson",
          "Harold II",
          "Godwinson"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this venue on New Years Eve 1989, David Hasselhoff performed his hit song Looking for Freedom.\nThis location was home to My God, Help Me To Survive This Deadly Love, a depiction of Brezhnev and\nHonecker embracing, in its East Side Gallery. Due to poor grammar, John F. Kennedy awkwardly claimed\nto be a donut after this structure was built, and Ronald Reagan appealed to “Mr. Gorbachev” to tear it\ndown. For ten points, name this structure that fell in 1989, reuniting the German capital city.",
        "answer": [
          "Berlin Wall",
          "Berliner Mauer"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This late British rock musician said “We send our wishes to all our friends who are on the other\nside of the wall” when performing his song Heroes at the Berlin Wall in 1987.",
        "answer": [
          "David Bowie",
          "Bowie",
          "David Robert Jones",
          "Jones"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this empire, people or land could be granted a form of quasi-sovereignty called immediacy. In 1500,\nthis empire was reformed into a series of six Circles, including the Swabian Circle. This empire’s rulers\nincluded Henry IV, who feuded with Gregory VII during the Investiture Controversy, and a ruler who\ndefeated the Magyars at Lechfeld. Otto the Great led, for ten points, what patchwork of states located in\nmodern-day Germany, whose emperor was crowned by the Pope in Rome?",
        "answer": [
          "Holy Roman Empire",
          "Holy Roman",
          "HRE"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Holy Roman Emperor tried to subjugate the Italian states before drowning in the Saleph\nRiver during the Third Crusade.",
        "answer": [
          "Frederick Barbarossa",
          "Barbarossa",
          "Frederick I"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This organization ran the Addiscombe College for prospective officers in the Presidency armies. This\norganization was opposed by governors called Polygars. This organization was opposed by Tipu Sultan,\nwho fought four Mysore Wars against it. Its ascent to power began after Robert Clive won the Battle of\nPlassey against the Nawab of Bengal, who had orchestrated the Black Hole of Calcutta. For ten points,\nname this joint stock company that conquered most of the Indian subcontinent for England.",
        "answer": [
          "British East India Company",
          "British East India"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The British East India Company lost control of India after this event, in which Indian soldiers\nrevolted after being given rifle cartridges greased with animal fats.",
        "answer": [
          "Sepoy Mutiny",
          "Sepoy",
          "Indian Rebellion of 1857"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Adolphe Thiers’ [tee-ayrz] desire to establish this river as a border led to an 1840 crisis. A bridge over\nthis river at Remagen was notably captured intact by American forces during World War II. Operation\nMarket Garden was a failed attempt to cross this river, which passes by the heavily industrialized Ruhr\nregion. A capital city on this river was Bonn, and this river served with the Danube as the northern\nborder of the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this prominent river in western Germany.",
        "answer": [
          "Rhine River",
          "Rhine"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Rhineland surrounding the river was subject to Allied occupation and this other condition\nafter the Treaty of Versailles. Hitler’s violation of this condition was met with appeasement from France\nand Germany.",
        "answer": [
          "demilitarisation",
          "forbidding military activity",
          "decreasing military activity",
          "demilitarization"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country formed after the union of a namesake duchy, Styria, and Carinthia. The Privilegium\nMaius gave this country the title of Archduchy. This country came into constant conflict with the Ottomans\nover territories in Transylvania. Klemens von Metternich led a peace conference in this country’s capital\nin 1814. For ten points, name this country that was ruled by the Habsburgs, joined in a Dual Monarchy\nwith Hungary, and hosted the Congress of Vienna.",
        "answer": [
          "Austria",
          "Osterreich"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Congress of Vienna was largely dictated by one of these political alliances. The Seventh of\nthese fought Napoleon during the Hundred Days, while the defeat of the Third one led to the dissolution\nof the Holy Roman Empire.",
        "answer": [
          "coalitions",
          "Seventh Coalition",
          "Third Coalition"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After the death of this country’s King Alexander I, it was ruled by the regent Prince Paul. One\nconflict after the fall of this country was ended by the Dayton Accords. One of its rulers was thrown out\nof the Cominform by Stalin, and had led the Partisans in this country to oppose Nazi Germany. This\ncountry’s collapse in the 1990s led to multiple independence wars, which included the Siege of Sarajevo\nas part of the Bosnian War. For ten points, name this multiethnic state that was ruled by Tito, whose\nconstituent states included Croatia and Serbia.",
        "answer": [
          "Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia",
          "Yugoslavia",
          "Kingdom of Yugoslavia",
          "Kingdom of Serbs Croats and Slovenes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This territory attempted to break free from Serbia during the Yugoslav Wars. NATO bombed\nSerbian forces in this state, which is only recognized as an independent country by about half of the world.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Kosovo",
          "Kosovo"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two Partition Treaties were signed to prevent this war, while the Barrier Treaties allowed one of the\nvictors to set up a series of forts as a buffer. The capture of Port Royal in Acadia occurred in its North\nAmerican theater, which was called Queen Anne’s War. Great Britain gained Gibraltar after this war,\nduring which Marshal Tallard was crushed at the Battle of Blenheim [BLEN-um]. This war began after\nthe death of the childless Charles II and the proposed accession of Phillip of Anjou. For ten points, name\nthis war, ended by the Treaty of Utrecht, fought over the throne of the namesake Iberian nation.",
        "answer": [
          "War of the Spanish Succession",
          "Spanish Succession"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The military success of the alliance against France was mostly due to these two generals, who\nworked together at Blenheim and Malplaquet. Name either.",
        "answer": [
          "Eugene of Savoy",
          "Duke of Marlborough",
          "Marlborough",
          "John Churchill"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An insurrection in this state was fought by the Milice. This state was the site of the Drancy\nconcentration camp. Its territory was known as a “free zone,” and it adopted the slogan “Work, Family,\nFatherland.” Prime Minister Pierre Laval led this state, which was able to scuttle its fleet in Toulon\nHarbor to prevent their re-occupiers from seizing the ships. For ten points, name this puppet government\nthat ruled part of France alongside Nazi Germany during World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Vichy France",
          "Vichy",
          "French State"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Vichy France’s president was this World War I hero who led French forces at Verdun.",
        "answer": [
          "Henri-Philippe Petain",
          "Petain",
          "Philippe Petain"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was divided into themes, which each supplied a portion of troops, until they were\nsupplemented by the tagmata system. The Latin Empire occupied the lands of this empire until the\nPalaiologos dynasty reclaimed the land. The Fourth Crusade ended in the sacking of this empire, whose\nEcumenical Patriarch served as religious head of this country’s Orthodox faith. For ten points, name this\nsuccessor state of the Roman Empire that was based in Constantinople until 1453.",
        "answer": [
          "Byzantine Empire",
          "Byzantine",
          "Eastern Roman Empire",
          "Eastern Roman"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Byzantine Empire’s navy used this incendiary weapon. Its recipe is lost, but it was notable\nfor being able to burn on water.",
        "answer": "Greek fire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This party was founded by the Tamworth Manifesto, and it provided the vast majority of seats for\nthe first National Government. It came to power after the Winter of Discontent, and it won the “Coupon”\nelection of 1918 under David Lloyd George. Under Balfour and Disraeli, this party opposed the Liberals in\nthe 19th century, and its 20th century prime ministers included Margaret Thatcher and Winston Churchill.\nFor ten points, name this center-right party that opposes Labour in the modern United Kingdom.",
        "answer": [
          "Conservative and Unionist Party",
          "Conservative",
          "Tory Party",
          "Tory"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man is largely considered to be the founder of the Conservatives. He introduced the first\nmodern police force and repealed the Corn Laws.",
        "answer": [
          "Sir Robert Peel",
          "Peel"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. The secret 1915 Treaty of London supported this goal via a promise regarding\nSouth Tyrol. A group of quick infantry known as the Bersaglieri fought for this goal. The Expedition of\nthe Thousand was made in support of this goal, which was engineered by Count Cavour and Giuseppe\nGaribaldi. For ten points, name this 19th century nationalist process, known as the Risorgimento, which\nformed a modern country with its capital at Rome.",
        "answer": [
          "Italian unification",
          "Italy becoming a unified country",
          "Italy unified"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Count Cavour served as Prime Minister of this pre-unification kingdom, whose capital was at\nTurin. Its king, Victor Emmanuel, became the first King of Italy.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia",
          "Piedmont-Sardinia",
          "Piedmont Sardinia",
          "Piedmont",
          "Sardinia"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A civil war during this conflict was fought between the Armagnacs and Burgundians. One side of\nthis war sent out cavalry raids called chevauch´ees [sheh-voh-SHAYS], sometimes led by the Black Prince.\nCharles VII was crowned after this war’s Siege of Orleans was lifted. Longbows helped the English win\nthe Battle of Crecy during, for ten points, what war between England and France that lasted from 1337\nto 1453?",
        "answer": [
          "Hundred Years’ War",
          "Hundred Years’"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Siege of Orleans was lifted with the help of this 17-year-old French peasant girl. She was\ncaptured and burned at the stake by the English, but cleared by the Pope years later and made a saint in\n1920.",
        "answer": [
          "Saint Joan of Arc",
          "Joan of Arc",
          "Saint Jeanne d'Arc",
          "Jeanne d'Arc"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This kingdom allowed Janos Hunyadi to serve as regent despite losing at the Battle of Varna. The\nethnic group that founded this kingdom raided Europe before their defeat by Holy Roman Emperor\nOtto I at Lechfeld and are known as the Magyars. This kingdom came into personal unions with nearby\nCroatia, Austria, and Bohemia and is surrounded by the Carpathian Mountains. For ten points, name\nthis kingdom that ruled from what is now Budapest.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Hungary",
          "Hungary"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hungary was eventually split by the Habsburgs, the Ottomans, and this third independent state\nruled by John Zapolya. Bram Stoker’s Count Dracula came from this region.",
        "answer": "Transylvania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this Prime Minister’s tenure, the Sun ran an infamous headline declaring “Gotcha!” after\na submarine controversially sunk the enemy ship General Belgrano in international waters. The IRA\nattempted to assassinate this Conservative leader in the Brighton Hotel Bombing. John Major succeeded,\nfor ten points, what “Iron Lady” who led through the 1980s as the UK’s first female Prime Minister?",
        "answer": [
          "Margaret Hilda Thatcher",
          "Thatcher",
          "Margaret Thatcher"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The General Belgrano was sunk during a 1982 war between Britain and Argentina over this\nSouth Atlantic island chain",
        "answer": [
          "Falkland Islands",
          "Falklands",
          "Islas Malvinas",
          "Malvinas"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this king’s finance minister liberalized grain commerce, the ensuing grain hoarding triggered\nrevolts known as the Flour War; this king then dismissed that minister, Turgot [tur-goh], in favor of\nJacques Necker. This king, who sent the Comte de Rochambeau to aid the American Revolution, was\ncaught fleeing to Varennes with his wife, Marie Antoinette. For ten points, name this French king who\nwas executed during the French Revolution.",
        "answer": "Louis XVI"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Louis XVI was executed shortly before the Reign of Terror, which was orchestrated by this\nleader of the Committee of Public Safety.",
        "answer": [
          "Maximilien Robespierre",
          "Robespierre"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two answers required. These two countries fought the Battle of Pinkie, which became known as\n“Black Saturday” on the losing side. In the largest clash between these two countries, the invading side\nlost their king at Flodden Field. A queen of one of these countries was implicated in the Babington Plot\nand executed by the other’s queen, Elizabeth I. For ten points, name these two countries that were unified\nin 1707 and share a border on the isle of Great Britain.",
        "answer": "Scotland and England"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned Battle of Flodden Field was instigated by Scotland, which invaded England\nto uphold its end of the Auld Alliance with this European country.",
        "answer": "France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1966, Secretary of State Dean Rusk asked this leader if a recent order applied to American soldiers\nin his country’s cemeteries. Lester Pearson noted that “Canadians do not need to be liberated” in his\ncriticism of this man’s declaration of “vive le Quebec libre.” This leader signed the Evian Accords, leading\nto the independence of Algeria. For ten points, name this first president of the Fifth Republic who led\nFree France in World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Charles de Gaulle",
          "de Gaulle"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1966, de Gaulle pulled France out of this organization’s Military Command Structure and\nordered foreign soldiers to leave France, leading to Rusk’s aforementioned question. France fully returned\nto this military alliance in 2009.",
        "answer": [
          "NATO",
          "North Atlantic Treaty Organization"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The third of these people died shortly after giving birth to a son whose betrothal ended the War of the\nRough Wooing. The fourth of these people was known as the “King’s Beloved Sister” because she never\nconsummated her marriage; that woman was Anne of Cleves. Clement VII refused to annul a marriage\ninvolving one of these women, leading to the creation of the Anglican Church. Catherine of Aragon was\nthe first of, for ten points, what group of six women married to an English king?",
        "answer": "wives of Henry VIII"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned third wife of Henry VIII was this woman, the mother of Edward VI. She is\nthe only one of Henry’s wives not named Anne or Catherine.",
        "answer": [
          "Jane Seymour",
          "Seymour"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE CONGRESS OF VIENNA",
      "prompt": "During or after the Congress of Vienna, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French emperor was exiled to Saint Helena?",
          "answer": [
            "Napoleon Bonaparte",
            "Napoleon",
            "Napoleon I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian statesmen hosted the forum?",
          "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who was victorious at Waterloo joined Castlereagh in representing the UK?",
          "answer": [
            "Arthur Wellesley",
            "Wellesley",
            "the Duke of Wellington",
            "Wellington"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Czar of Russia led the Russian delegation?",
          "answer": "Alexander I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country retained control of the Cape Colony and Tobago?",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Minister for Louis XVIII headed the French delegation?",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Maurice de Talleyrand",
            "Talleyrand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country regained control of Tyrol and Ragusa?",
          "answer": "Austria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country was represented by Cael Lowenhielm, an illegitimate son of its king Charles XIII?",
          "answer": "Sweden"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MEDIEVAL EASTERN EUROPE",
      "prompt": "In the Middle Ages, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire which, by the 1070s, was reduced to the area around Constantinople?",
          "answer": "Byzantine, Byzantine Empire, Eastern Roman Empire, Eastern Roman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country first organized by the Piast Dynasty, which was later invaded by its neighbor\nGermany to start World War II?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim empire based in Turkey which conquered much of the region from 1308 to 1571?",
          "answer": "Ottoman, Ottoman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country where the Grand Duchy of Muscovy formed around the city of Moscow?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group which briefly overran Eastern Europe after defeating the Hungarians at Mohi in 1241?",
          "answer": "Mongol, Mongols"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Vladimir the Great converted a namesake state to Christianity before it became the\nUkrainian capital?",
          "answer": "Kiev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince of Wallachia (pr. wah-LAY-kee-uh) whose practice of putting opposing soldiers on\nstakes inspired vampire legends?",
          "answer": "Vlad the Impaler, Vlad Dracula, Dracula, Vlad III, Vlad Tepes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle, which shares its name with a Balkan country that declared independence in 2008 from\nSerbia?",
          "answer": "Kosovo"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CHARLEMAGNE",
      "prompt": "Medieval emperor Charlemagne...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was crowned on Christmas 800 by Leo III, a holder of what top office of the Catholic\nChurch?",
          "answer": "Pope, the Papacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Instigated the \"Carolingian\" example of what sort of period in which arts and learning revive?",
          "answer": "renaissance"
        },
        {
          "question": "Launched a crusade against what Germanic people, who earlier joined with the Angles to\nconquer England?",
          "answer": "Saxons"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 797, took control of what currently second largest city in Spain?",
          "answer": "Barcelona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the son of what small-statured king?",
          "answer": "Pepin the Short, Pepin III, Pepin le Bref, Pippin der Kurze"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was gifted what kind of large animal, known as Abul-Abbas, by the Abbasid caliph?",
          "answer": "elephant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of which Germanic tribe who were earlier led by the Merovingians?",
          "answer": "Franks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the grandson of what Mayor of the Palace who won the Battle of Tours?",
          "answer": "Charles Martel, Carolus Martellus, Karl Martell"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THIRTY YEARS WAR",
      "prompt": "During the Thirty Years War, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Increasingly chaotic German “empire” whose member states took opposing sides?",
          "answer": [
            "Holy Roman Empire",
            "Holy Roman",
            "Hapsburg Empire",
            "Hapsburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Major world religion whose Protestant Reformation was one of the war’s ultimate causes?",
          "answer": "Christianity"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty which formally ended the conflict?",
          "answer": [
            "Peace of Westphalia",
            "Westphalia",
            "Munster",
            "Osnabruck",
            "Treaty of Westphalia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Activity which peaked during the war, and used the Malleus Mallificarum to determine whom to\nburn?",
          "answer": [
            "witch-hunts",
            "witch",
            "witch-hunting"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose pragmatic policy was made by Cardinal Richelieu (pr. ree-shell-OO)?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Event in which two diplomats were thrown out a window that sparked the fighting?",
          "answer": "Defenestration of Prague"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Sweden who was killed at the Battle of Lutzen?",
          "answer": [
            "Gustavus Adolphus",
            "Gustav II",
            "Gustav Adolf"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Watershed historical year in which it ended?",
          "answer": "1648"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE U.K. IN THE 1990’S",
      "prompt": "In the 1990s, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City where the Jubilee underground line on the tube was extended?",
          "answer": "London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holiday shortly before Easter for which a Northern Ireland peace accord was named?",
          "answer": "Good Friday"
        },
        {
          "question": "Labour Party Prime Minister who began his ten-year term in 1997?",
          "answer": [
            "Tony Blair",
            "Blair",
            "Anthony Charles Lynton Blair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose “United” soccer team was managed by Sir Alex Ferguson?",
          "answer": "Manchester"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where a Scottish parliament was established?",
          "answer": "Edinburgh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longtime Chancellor of the Exchequer who ultimately succeeded to the premiership in 2007?",
          "answer": [
            "Gordon Brown",
            "Brown"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Five-member \"girl group\" whose song \"Wannabe\" led the British pop culture revival?",
          "answer": "The Spice Girls"
        },
        {
          "question": "1992 treaty creating the European Union which Britain joined?",
          "answer": [
            "Maastricht Treaty",
            "Maastricht"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CRUSADES",
      "prompt": "In the era of the Crusades, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Religion whose Crusaders sought to capture Jerusalem from Muslim Turks?",
          "answer": [
            "Christianity",
            "Christian",
            "Roman Catholicism",
            "Catholic",
            "Catholicism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group which was the target of pogroms in the Rhineland at the hands of the People's\nCrusade?",
          "answer": "Jews"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of England who left his brother John in charge while he led the Third Crusade?",
          "answer": [
            "Richard the Lionheart",
            "Richard I",
            "Richard Coeur de Lion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kurdish founder of the Ayyubid (pr. eye-OO-bid) Dynasty who was the opponent of the\nThird Crusade?",
          "answer": [
            "Saladin",
            "Salah al-Din"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea across which Crusaders sailed to the Holy Land?",
          "answer": [
            "Mediterranean Sea",
            "Mediterranean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of defensive building, such as Krak des Chevaliers (pr. KRAG doo shoo-vahl-YAY),\noften constructed by Crusaders?",
          "answer": [
            "castles"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who called for the First Crusade?",
          "answer": "Urban II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crusade which descended into looting and sacked Constantinople?",
          "answer": [
            "Fourth Crusade",
            "Fourth"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EMANCIPATION OF SERFS",
      "prompt": "The emancipation of the world's largest serf population...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Occurred in what empire, which was ultimately ended by the deposition of Tsar Nicholas II?",
          "answer": [
            "Russian Empire",
            "Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Began in what year, also the year Abraham Lincoln's Presidency and the Civil War started?",
          "answer": "1861"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was instigated by what tsar, who was assassinated twenty years later?",
          "answer": "Alexander II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ended the landlord veto over serfs engaging in what practice, the subject of the American\ncourt case Loving v. Virginia?",
          "answer": [
            "marriage",
            "weddings"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was part of the fallout from Russia's defeat by Britain, France, and Turkey in what war?",
          "answer": [
            "Crimean War",
            "Crimean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led radicals to support what political position that characterized the Nechaevists, Land and\nLiberty, and The People's Will?",
          "answer": [
            "anarchism",
            "nihilism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Set up what system of elected provincial councils?",
          "answer": [
            "zemstvos"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Required that former serfs do what for forty-nine years?",
          "answer": [
            "submit redemption payments to former owners",
            "redemption payment"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "VICTORIAN SOCIETY",
      "prompt": "In England during the time of Queen Victoria, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Author of A Christmas Carol and Great Expectations who complained about social\nconditions?",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Dickens",
            "Dickens"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Long-term economic phenomenon in which mechanized factories became the dominant sector\nof the economy?",
          "answer": "Industrial Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Serial killer who targeted prostitutes in London in 1888?",
          "answer": "Jack the Ripper"
        },
        {
          "question": "Major British possession in Asia, which Victoria was declared Empress of?",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that was the world’s most populous throughout Victoria’s reign?",
          "answer": "London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conservative Party leader whom Victoria favored over his rival Gladstone?",
          "answer": [
            "Benjamin Disraeli",
            "Disraeli"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Playwright and author of The Picture of Dorian Grey who was sentenced to jail for his\nsexuality?",
          "answer": [
            "Oscar Wilde",
            "Wilde"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Famous Crimean War era poem written by Tennyson about a disastrous cavalry mission?",
          "answer": "The Charge of the Light Brigade"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE SPANISH ARMADA",
      "prompt": "The Spanish Armada was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sent off in what historic year?",
          "answer": "1588"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempting to return England to what religion?",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Catholicism",
            "Catholic",
            "Catholicism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sent against what Queen of England?",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Funded in part by Spanish conquests over what Native Americans of the Andes Mountains?",
          "answer": [
            "Incans",
            "Incas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Initially combatted by what commander of the Golden Hind?",
          "answer": [
            "Francis Drake",
            "Drake"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Shattered near the Munster and Connacht (pr. cuh-NOKT) areas of what island when it was\nblown off course on its return?",
          "answer": "Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organized by what Spanish king?",
          "answer": "Philip II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unsuccessfully commanded by what Spanish military officer?",
          "answer": [
            "Duke of Medina Sidonia",
            "Medina Sidonia",
            "Don Alonso Perez de Guzman y de Zuniga-Sotomayor",
            "Guzman"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "WORLD WAR I",
      "prompt": "In World War I, who or what was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The country which exited the war following the Bolshevik Revolution and organized the\nUSSR five years later?",
          "answer": [
            "Russia",
            "Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic",
            "Soviet Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The palace outside Paris where the main peace treaty was signed?",
          "answer": "Versailles"
        },
        {
          "question": "The archduke whose assassination sparked the conflict?",
          "answer": [
            "Franz Ferdinand",
            "Francis Ferdinand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The assassin responsible for that archduke's death?",
          "answer": [
            "Gavrilo Princip",
            "Princip"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The country whose violated neutrality was a proximate cause of Britain’s entering the war?",
          "answer": "Belgium"
        },
        {
          "question": "The high commander of American forces in the war?",
          "answer": [
            "John Pershing",
            "John Joseph Pershing",
            "Pershing",
            "Black Jack Pershing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The German war plan which involved quickly defeating France before fighting Russia?",
          "answer": [
            "Schlieffen Plan",
            "Schlieffen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The August 1914 battle where Hindenburg and Ludendorff destroyed a Russian army?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Tannenberg",
            "Tannenberg"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MUSSOLINI",
      "prompt": "Benito Mussolini...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the dictator of what country?",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Promoted what ideology named for a Roman bundle of sticks?",
          "answer": "fascism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Took on what title meaning \"leader?\"",
          "answer": [
            "Il Duce",
            "Duce"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Authorized the invasion of what African country in 1935, displacing Haile Selassie (hai-LEH\nse-lah-SEE)?",
          "answer": [
            "Ethiopia",
            "Abyssinia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Entered what agreement in May 1939, formally creating the Axis?",
          "answer": [
            "Pact of Steel",
            "Stahlpakt",
            "Patto d'Acciaio"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the invasion of what country in 1939, causing the overthrow of King Zog?",
          "answer": "Albania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed trying to flee to which country that borders Italy?",
          "answer": "Switzerland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Eventually was hung upside down outside a gas station in which largest Northern Itailan city?",
          "answer": "Milan"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE SOUTH SEA BUBBLE",
      "prompt": "England's South Sea Bubble scandal of 1720...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Arose over a company which transported what kind of people in the \"Middle Passage\" after\nforcible abduction from Africa?",
          "answer": [
            "slaves"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led to the creation of what office, later held by Margaret Thatcher and David Cameron?",
          "answer": [
            "Prime Minister of the United Kingdom",
            "Prime Minister",
            "First Lord of the Treasury"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Occurred during the reign of what first Hanoverian king?",
          "answer": "George I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led to the ascension of what party, which opposed the Tories in the eighteenth-century British\nparty system?",
          "answer": [
            "Whigs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Temporarily soured the English investor class on what form of business entity which preceded\ncorporations and was prominent during the Age of Exploration?",
          "answer": "joint-stock company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arose from an attempt to exploit the Treaty of Utrecht, which ended what war in 1713?",
          "answer": [
            "War of the Spanish Succession",
            "Spanish Succession"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was resolved by what politician who dominated the British government until 1742?",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Walpole",
            "Walpole"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Caused the creation of what institution, which manages UK monetary policy?",
          "answer": "Bank of England"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "POST-WAR ITALY",
      "prompt": "In Italy after World War II, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ideology advocated by the Red Brigades terrorist group and Italy's neighbor Yugoslavia?",
          "answer": [
            "Communism",
            "Marxism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Organized crime phenomenon which was curtailed in the \"Maxi trial?\"",
          "answer": "the mafia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization formed by the Maastricht Treaty which Italy was an architect of?",
          "answer": [
            "European Union",
            "EU"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Western military alliance which orchestrated Operation Gladio in Italy?",
          "answer": [
            "NATO",
            "North Atlantic Treaty Organization"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Media mogul who became Italy's right-wing prime minister three times and was frequently\ncharged with corruption?",
          "answer": [
            "Silvio Berlusconi",
            "Berlusconi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Milan-based designer who founded what is now Italy's largest men's fashion house in 1975?",
          "answer": [
            "Giorgio Armani",
            "Armani"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Umbrella auto manufacturer which now owns Ferrari, Maserati, and Chrysler?",
          "answer": "Fiat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name commonly given to the period of political violence from 1969 to the mid-1980s?",
          "answer": [
            "Years of Lead",
            "Anni di piombo"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE COURT OF THE FRENCH KING",
      "prompt": "What important person in the reigns of the final four kings of pre-Revolutionary France was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "A radical free speech advocate and the author of Candide?",
          "answer": [
            "Voltaire",
            "Francois-Marie Arouet",
            "Arouet"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "A finance minister whose cheapness caused his name to be applied to an all-black outline\nportrait?",
          "answer": [
            "Etienne de Silhouette",
            "Silhouette"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The king from 1610 to 1643 who ended the regency of Marie de Medici?",
          "answer": "Louis XIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "The thinker who explained separation of powers in The Spirit of the Laws?",
          "answer": [
            "Baron Montesquieu",
            "Charles-Louis de Secondat",
            "Secondat"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Catholic \"Red Eminence\" who dominated the court in the 1620s and 30s?",
          "answer": [
            "Cardinal Richelieu",
            "Richelieu",
            "Armand Jean du Plessis",
            "du Plessis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The influential mistress of Louis XV with a flamboyant hairstyle?",
          "answer": [
            "Madame de Pompadour",
            "Pompadour"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The formulator of the law of conservation of mass and the metric system who was executed by\nthe Revolution despite being the \"Father of Modern Chemistry?\"",
          "answer": [
            "Antoine Lavoisier",
            "Lavoisier"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The composer of religious music for Louis XIV who died after shattering his foot with a\nbaton?",
          "answer": [
            "Jean-Baptiste Lully",
            "Lully"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EASTERN EUROPEAN COUNTRIES",
      "prompt": "Which Eastern European country...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Unified the cities of Buda and Pest in 1873?",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was in a union with Montenegro until 2006?",
          "answer": "Serbia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Broke away from the Czech Republic in 1993?",
          "answer": "Slovakia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had 7 border guards killed in a Soviet assault near Vilnius?",
          "answer": "Lithuania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to electrician, politician, and Nobel Peace Prize winner Lech Walesa [vah-WE-sa]?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the modern site of the former capital of the Kievan Rus?",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saw its leader, Nicolae Ceausescu [CHO-ses-koo], executed for war crimes in a 1989 revolution?",
          "answer": "Romania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was considered the “last dictatorship in Europe” under Alexander Lukashenko?",
          "answer": "Belarus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "GERMAN CULTURE",
      "prompt": "What is...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The once-divided German capital city?",
          "answer": "Berlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Christian holiday celebrated with street markets called Weihnachtsmarkt [VYE-nakts-markt]\nand advent calendars?",
          "answer": [
            "Christmas",
            "Christmas Eve",
            "Christmas Day"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The sibling storytellers of fairy tales like Hansel and Gretel?",
          "answer": [
            "Brothers Grimm",
            "Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm",
            "Grimm"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The highway system whose efficiency and lack of speed limits inspired President Eisenhower?",
          "answer": "Autobahn"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Bavarian capital city whose beer halls sponsor the annual Oktoberfest?",
          "answer": "Munich"
        },
        {
          "question": "The NBA MVP who has played 17 seasons for the Dallas Mavericks?",
          "answer": [
            "Dirk Nowitzki",
            "Nowitzki"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The founder of the Bayreuth [bye-ROYT] opera house, where his Ring Cycle is annually performed?",
          "answer": [
            "Richard Wagner",
            "Wagner"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The German art and architecture school founded by Walter Gropius?",
          "answer": "Bauhaus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MODERN BRITISH PMS",
      "prompt": "Which British Prime Minister from the 20th and 21st centuries...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is the current PM (2025)?",
          "answer": "Keir Starmer"
        },
        {
          "question": "served during most of World War II, offering nothing but “blood, toil, tears, and sweat?”",
          "answer": [
            "Winston Churchill",
            "Churchill"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was known as the Iron Lady?",
          "answer": [
            "Margaret Thatcher",
            "Thatcher"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "attended the 1919 Paris Peace Conference and helped organize the Treaty of Versailles?",
          "answer": [
            "David Lloyd George",
            "Lloyd George"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "signed the Munich Agreement with Hitler, proclaiming “peace in our time”?",
          "answer": [
            "Neville Chamberlain",
            "Chamberlain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "replaced his predecessor as the new Labour PM at the 1945 Potsdam Conference?",
          "answer": [
            "Clement Attlee",
            "Attlee"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was criticized for sending troops to Iraq in 2003?",
          "answer": [
            "Tony Blair",
            "Blair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was comparably less criticized for sending troops to Iraq in 1991?",
          "answer": [
            "John Major",
            "Major"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BYZANTINE EMPIRE",
      "prompt": "In the history of the Byzantine Empire, who or what was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Its capital city, originally known as Byzantium and now known as Istanbul?",
          "answer": "Constantinople"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Italian city whose empire it continued in the east?",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "The empire that arose after conquering the Byzantine Empire, which lasted until World War 1?",
          "answer": [
            "Ottoman Empire",
            "Ottoman"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The official monotheistic religion of the empire, after a decree by Theodosius?",
          "answer": [
            "Christianity",
            "Orthodox Christianity"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The religious images banned by Leo III in the 8th century?",
          "answer": [
            "Icons",
            "Iconoclasm"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Germanic tribe conquered by Belisarius in north Africa, whose name now refers to general destruction\nof property?",
          "answer": [
            "Vandals",
            "vandalism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The wife of Justinian who convinced him not to flee from the Nika Riots?",
          "answer": "Theodora"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Ottoman sultan who conquered Constantinople in 1453, ending the Byzantine Empire?",
          "answer": [
            "Mehmed II",
            "Mehmed the Conqueror"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE INQUISITION",
      "prompt": "In the history of the Inquisition, who or what is...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The Iberian country for which it is often named, home to cities such as Castille?",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "The religion of the Moors, who were simultaneously being expelled from the Iberian Peninsula in the\nReconquista?",
          "answer": [
            "Islam",
            "Muslims"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The other commonly persecuted religion during the Inquisition, who were expelled by the Alhambra\nDecree?",
          "answer": [
            "Judaism",
            "Jews",
            "Jewish"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The other Iberian country to which the Inquisition spread?",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "The term for public penance by the condemned, usually in the form of a public burning?",
          "answer": "auto da fe"
        },
        {
          "question": "The torture device in which a victim’s wrists and ankles are strapped to a frame and gradually pulled\napart?",
          "answer": [
            "torture rack",
            "rack"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The base city for Tomas de Torquemada’s first tribunal?",
          "answer": "Seville"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Dostoyevsky novel in which, in a parable, Christ is confronted by Grand Inquisitor Torquemada?",
          "answer": "The Brothers Karamazov"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EUROPEAN NAVIES",
      "prompt": "In European naval history, what is...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The country whose Baltic Sea ports include Kaliningrad and St. Petersburg?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The term for German submarines that harassed Allied shipping during World Wars 1 and 2?",
          "answer": [
            "U-boats",
            "Unterseeboots",
            "U boats"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The fleet of over 100 ships whose invasion of England was thwarted by Francis Drake?",
          "answer": "Spanish Armada"
        },
        {
          "question": "The country that has naval yards at Szczecin [st-etch-in] and Gdansk?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "The battle at which Lord Nelson died?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Trafalgar",
            "Trafalgar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The French city where British fishing boats and little ships ferried evacuated Allied soldiers from the\nNazis?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Dunkirk",
            "Dunkirk"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The October 1571 galley battle in which the Holy League devastated an Ottoman fleet in the Ionian\nSea?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Lepanto",
            "Lepanto"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Nazi operation that would have invaded Britain if naval superiority had been achieved?",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Sealion",
            "Sealion"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "COUNTRIES IN WORLD WAR II",
      "prompt": "In World War II, which country...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was allied with Germany until the Allies invaded it and captured Rome?",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first to be invaded by Germany, on September 1, 1939?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created the Maginot Line to defend against Germany, but quickly surrendered anyway?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was invaded by Nazi Germany during Operation Barbarossa and later captured Berlin?",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "USSR",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "CCCP",
            "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Allied with Germany after it lost the Winter War?",
          "answer": "Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a German invasion at Trondheim, and was led by Vidkun Quisling?",
          "answer": "Norway"
        },
        {
          "question": "Maintained a policy of neutrality while buying stolen German gold?",
          "answer": "Switzerland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Eastern European site of the Ploiesti [ploy-esh-tee] oilfields, vital to the Nazi war effort?",
          "answer": "Romania"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "QUEENS OF EUROPE",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Longest reigning monarch of the United Kingdom.",
          "answer": [
            "Elizabeth II",
            "Queen Elizabeth II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Iberian country ruled by just two queens named Maria, who also ruled over Brazil.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pious queen of Castile who authorized the first Spanish colonization efforts and was married to\nFerdinand of Aragon.",
          "answer": [
            "Isabella",
            "Isabella I of Castile",
            "Isabella I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Beheaded queen who legendarily said “Let them eat cake!”",
          "answer": "Marie Antoniette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Stuart queen who tried to overthrow Elizabeth I and was subsequently executed.",
          "answer": [
            "Mary Queen of Scots",
            "Mary I of Scotland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Low country in Northern Europe ruled by Queen Beatrix in the 20th century.",
          "answer": [
            "the Netherlands",
            "Holland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Position held by two of Henry VIII’s queens, who governed in place of a monarch who cannot rule\ndue to absence, sickness, or youth.",
          "answer": [
            "Queen regent",
            "regent"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Duchess of Aquitaine who became Queen of both England and France and helped form the Angevin\nEmpire.",
          "answer": [
            "Eleanor of Aquitaine",
            "Eleanor"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ENGLISH CIVIL WAR",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "English legislature that fought against the king and was reduced to “Rump” size by Pride’s Purge.",
          "answer": [
            "Rump Parliament",
            "Parliament"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Oliver Cromwell brutally suppressed Royalist soldiers from his base in Dublin.",
          "answer": "Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom to the north of England that repeatedly intervened in the conflict.",
          "answer": "Scotland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Stuart monarch executed during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Charles I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Title given to Oliver Cromwell after defeating the Royalists.",
          "answer": "Lord Protector"
        },
        {
          "question": "Document, originally written to protect 13th century barons, which was cited by the Petition of Right\nleading up to the War.",
          "answer": "Magna Carta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Army in which Cromwell served as cavalry leader during the Civil War.",
          "answer": [
            "New Model Army",
            "New Model"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cromwell’s superior in that army, the victorious general at the Battle of Naseby.",
          "answer": [
            "Sir Thomas Fairfax",
            "Fairfax"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CHARLES V, HOLY ROMAN EMPEROR",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Iberian kingdom where he ruled as “Charles I,” to the south of France.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Spain",
            "Spain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty that ruled the Holy Roman Empire for three centuries and included Charles V.",
          "answer": [
            "Habsburg Dynasty",
            "Habsburg",
            "House of Habsburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious movement that expressed discontent with the Catholic Church and began during his reign.",
          "answer": [
            "Protestant Reformation",
            "Reformation"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Landmark exploration project he supported by funding Ferdinand Magellan’s 1519 voyage.",
          "answer": [
            "circumnavigation of the world",
            "circumnavigation",
            "sailing around the world"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Action he took to voluntarily leave his various thrones, a few years before his death.",
          "answer": "abdication"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of religious institution where he lived for two years after leaving the throne.",
          "answer": "monastery"
        },
        {
          "question": "French king that fought Charles in the Italian Wars but was captured at Pavia.",
          "answer": "Francis I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Imperial city where, in 1555, Charles V and the Schmalkaldic League agreed to the principle of “cuius\nregio, eius religio.”",
          "answer": [
            "Peace of Augsburg",
            "Aubsburg"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "FRENCH ROYALTY",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Religious group persecuted by Louis the Ninth for charging interest on loans, an example of\nanti-Semitism.",
          "answer": [
            "Jewish people",
            "Jews"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountainous country east of France from which Louis the Twelfth hired many mercenaries.",
          "answer": "Switzerland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Shared name of cathedrals in Rheims, where many French kings were crowned, and Paris, which\ntranslates as “Our Lady.”",
          "answer": "Notre Dame"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lowest class of feudal society, whose peasant members were allowed by Louis the Tenth to buy their\nfreedom.",
          "answer": "serfs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Husband of Marie Antoinette.",
          "answer": [
            "Louis XVI",
            "Louis 16"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Duchy, once led by William the Conqueror, that Louis the Sixth tried to recover from England.",
          "answer": "Normandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom that failed to renew its Auld Alliance with France during the reign of Louis the Eleventh.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Scotland",
            "Scotland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty that rose to power after the death of Louis the Fifth, from which all subsequent French kings\nwere descended.",
          "answer": [
            "House of Capet",
            "Capet"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "POLAND",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Method used to determine its king until 1791, in which each noble cast a vote.",
          "answer": [
            "election",
            "elective monarchy",
            "elective"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion it converted to after the baptism of its king in 966 AD.",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Catholicism",
            "Catholicism",
            "Christianity"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City that Sigismund III made Poland’s capital in 1596, and which is still the capital today.",
          "answer": "Warsaw"
        },
        {
          "question": "The original capital of Poland, site of a university founded in 1364.",
          "answer": "Krakow"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of military unit it specialized in, including the use of winged hussars.",
          "answer": "cavalry"
        },
        {
          "question": "The duchy that united with Poland in 1569, which is now a separate country with capital at Vilnius.",
          "answer": "Lithuania"
        },
        {
          "question": "the Parliament of the Polish Kingdom, which was paralyzed by the liberum veto policy requiring\nunanimous votes.",
          "answer": "Sejm"
        },
        {
          "question": "Swedish dynastic house that ruled Poland under Sigismund III",
          "answer": [
            "House of Vasa",
            "Vasa"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EUROPEAN LEFTIST POLITICS",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Former largest socialist country in Europe, which collapsed into Russia and other countries in 1991.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "USSR",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "CCCP",
            "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorfully named political movement that, in numerous countries, is a left-leaning political party that\nseeks environmental reform and peace?",
          "answer": [
            "Green parties",
            "Green"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Faction of communists in Russia that split from the Mensheviks in 1903.",
          "answer": "Bolsheviks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Britain’s New Labour movement who served as Prime Minister from 1997-2007.",
          "answer": [
            "Tony Blair",
            "Blair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alliance of socialist countries in eastern Europe that was formed to oppose NATO.",
          "answer": [
            "Warsaw Pact",
            "Warsaw"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Radical government that took over Paris when under threat during the Franco-Prussian War.",
          "answer": [
            "Paris Commune",
            "Commune"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the style of social and economic policies in Scandinavia that combine capitalism with a\nstrong welfare state.",
          "answer": [
            "Nordic model",
            "Nordic",
            "Nordic economics",
            "Nordic democracy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First UK Labour Prime Minister, who was negatively affected by the forged Zinoviev letter.",
          "answer": [
            "Ramsay MacDonald",
            "Ramsay"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CASTLES",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Protective ditch, usually filled with water, surrounding many castles.",
          "answer": "moats"
        },
        {
          "question": "System of government that lent itself to castle-building, as relatively independent lords ruled over\ntheir lands from a castle and served a king.",
          "answer": [
            "feudalism",
            "feudal",
            "feudalist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Siege engines that used a counterweight to swing a projectile at castle walls.",
          "answer": "trebuchets"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese technological innovation that allowed for bombards and mortars, making castles largely\nobsolete by the 15th century.",
          "answer": "gunpowder"
        },
        {
          "question": "Castle built by William the Conqueror outside of London after his conquest of England. It is now a\nroyal residence.",
          "answer": [
            "Windsor Castle",
            "Windsor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“Mad” King of Bavaria who built Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-stein] Castle.",
          "answer": [
            "Ludwig II",
            "Ludwig"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Coastal region of France east of Brittany where motte-and-bailey castles were first developed.",
          "answer": "Normandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crusading group that occupied Krak des Chevaliers [she-vahl-yay] in Syria until 1271 before going to\nMalta.",
          "answer": [
            "Knights Hospitaller",
            "Hospitaller",
            "the Order of Knights of the Hospital of Saint John",
            "the Order of Knights of the Hospital of Saint John of Jerusalem",
            "the order of Hospitallers"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EUROPEAN REFUGEE CRISIS",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Large sea crossed by migrants fleeing Africa to Europe. Its ancient Roman name, Mare Nostrum,\nnames a 2014 rescue operation.",
          "answer": [
            "Mediterranean Sea",
            "Mediterranean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of 28 European nations that debated how to handle the refugee crisis.",
          "answer": "European Union"
        },
        {
          "question": "Middle Eastern country where civil war against Bashar al-Assad has displaced the most refugees.",
          "answer": "Syria"
        },
        {
          "question": "River for much of Serbia and Croatia’s border, making border control difficult, and which passes\nthrough four European capitals.",
          "answer": [
            "Danube River",
            "Danube"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek island, home of the ancient poet Sappho, to which Turkish refugees often cross.",
          "answer": "Lesbos"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Prime Minister Viktor Orban built a wire fence along the Serbian border.",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current Italian Prime Minister who wants to expand migrant-return policies.",
          "answer": [
            "Paolo Gentiloni",
            "Gentiloni"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French coastal city where a large “Jungle” camp housed refugees and migrants until October 2016.",
          "answer": "Calais"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "WORLD WAR I",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Soldier who was wounded at the Somme and blinded in a gas attack, then later led Nazi Germany.",
          "answer": [
            "Adolf Hitler",
            "Hitler"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Archduke of Austria-Hungary who was shot in Sarajevo in 1914.",
          "answer": [
            "Archduke Franz Ferdinand",
            "Franz Ferdinand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“Sick Man of Europe” that joined the Central Powers in October 1914.",
          "answer": [
            "Ottoman Empire",
            "Ottoman"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation that sent David Lloyd George to the Paris Peace Conference.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "United Kingdom",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1914 battle where the German advance was halted along a namesake river, leading to trench warfare.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of the Marne River",
            "Marne",
            "Battle of the Marne"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1915 Allied campaign that failed to take Anzac Cove and never reached Constantinople.",
          "answer": [
            "Gallipoli Campaign",
            "Gallipoli",
            "Dardanelles Campaign",
            "Dardanelles",
            "Battle of Canakkale",
            "Canakkale"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed German plan to capture Paris in six weeks by sweeping through Belgium.",
          "answer": [
            "Schlieffen Plan",
            "Schlieffen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1914 battle that caused Alexander Samsonov, the losing general, to commit suicide.",
          "answer": [
            "Second Battle of Tannenberg",
            "Tannenberg",
            "Battle of Tannenberg"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "JEWS IN EUROPE",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "3,000-year-old language, used to write most of the Tanakh, whose modern form has adopted numerous\nEuropean influences.",
          "answer": "Hebrew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighborhoods where minorities, like Jews in Nazi-controlled Warsaw, were forced to live.",
          "answer": "ghettoes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Occupation that Jews were often forced to take because they were not affected by the Catholic\nChurch’s ban on usury. Examples include the Rothschild family.",
          "answer": [
            "banker",
            "bank",
            "moneylender",
            "lender",
            "loans",
            "charging interest on loans"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for outbursts of violence against Jews in the Russian Empire.",
          "answer": "pogroms"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group that was often tolerant of Jews, since it classified them as dhimmi, or people of the\nbook.",
          "answer": [
            "Islam",
            "Muslims"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Decree issued by Ferdinand and Isabella that forced all Jews in Spain to either convert or flee into\nexile.",
          "answer": [
            "Alhambra Decree",
            "Alhambra"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "19th century “affair” in which a Jewish French army officer was falsely accused of treason.",
          "answer": [
            "Alfred Dreyfus affair",
            "Dreyfus",
            "Dreyfus affair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "12th century Jewish scholar born in Cordova who wrote a code of Jewish law called the Mishneh\nTorah.",
          "answer": [
            "Maimonides",
            "Moses ben Maimon",
            "ben Maimon"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person was the subject of a \"nullification trial\" convened by Calixtus III. This\nperson led troops that captured John Talbot at the Battle of Patay. After getting an\naudience with (20 pts) ",
        "Charles VII, this person correctly identified the disguised king. This hero\nof the Siege of (10 pts) ",
        "Orleans claimed to have visions of St. Michael and St. Margaret. For 10\npoints, name this woman who was burned at the stake after fighting for the French in the\nHundred Year's War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jon of Arc",
        "Joan Arc",
        "Jeanne d'Arc",
        "Jeanne Arc"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's central bank adopted a policy of “forward guidance” for future interest\nrates after the 2008 financial crisis. It froze Icelandic bank assets in 2008 after Iceland\nrefused to guarantee its banks' debts to creditors in this country. The Chancellor of the (20 pts) ",
        "Exchequer proposed large spending cuts in 2010 as part of the austerity program of its\nformer prime minister, (10 pts) ",
        "David Cameron. For 10 points, name this country whose\ngovernment nationalized the Royal Bank of Scotland."
      ],
      "answer": "United Kingdom"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roger Ascham described the use of this weapon in the manual Toxophilus, and it survived in the British army until World War II, when Jack Churchill killed a Nazi soldier with one of them. These weapons were sometimes named for the (20 pts) ",
        "Welsh people who invented them and perfected their use, and they were used to great effect by the English at (10 pts) ",
        "Agincourt (pr. AA-jin-core). For 10 points, name this six-foot-tall archery weapon which replaced the crossbow."
      ],
      "answer": "longbow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man won a Nobel Prize in Literature for his History of the English-Speaking Peoples. This man was First Lord of the Admiralty during the (20 pts) ",
        "Gallipoli disaster, though his \"wilderness years\" eventually ended and allowed him to make the \"we shall (10 pts) ",
        "fight them on the beaches\" speech. He was defeated in his first re-election bid by Clement Attlee. For 10 points, name this leader of the national unity government of the U.K. during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Winston Churchill, Churchill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this organization were represented in the Reichstag by the Centre Party. This organization was targeted by Adalbert von Falk's May Laws, part of the (20 pts) ",
        "Kulturkampf (pr. KOOL-tur-kompf) against it launched by Otto von Bismarck. A leader of this organization who was accused of turning a blind eye to the Holocaust was (10 pts) ",
        "Pius XII. For 10 points, name this organization which is the predominant Christian denomination in southern Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church, Catholic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This city was the site of a Church council held five years before the Council of Constance which elected Alexander V as Pope in an attempt to end the Western Schism. This city was the loser of the Battle of (20 pts) ",
        "Meloria, and it was where a man allegedly dropped (10 pts) ",
        "cannonballs out of a window in order to measure acceleration. For 10 points, name this home to a gravitational experiment by Galileo, who made use of an architectural blunder that created its \"leaning tower.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Pisa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A person by this name was the fanatically Catholic Duke of Guise (pr. GHEEZ) while\nanother man of this name was the final king of the Valois (pr. val-WAH) Dynasty. Another\nman of this name was originally the king of (20 pts) ",
        "Navarre and said \"Paris is worth a mass\" to\nexplain his conversion to Catholicism. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, give this name of three men who fought\nthe last French War of Religion, including the first Bourbon king of France."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Henry",
        "Henri"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man led a legion in support of the Colorado Party during the Uruguayan Civil War.\nHe later took command of the Hunters of the Alps to fight against Austria, which challenged\nhis project that included the Siege of (20 pts) ",
        "Gaeta undertaken by the Expedition of the\nThousand. This man allied with Count (10 pts) ",
        "Cavour to achieve the Risorgimento (pr. reeSORGE-ee-MEN-toe). For 10 points, name this general who led the Redshirts on a successful\ncampaign to unify Italy."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Giuseppe Garibaldi",
        "Garibaldi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man revised the pamphlet The Falsifiers of History to present his side of 1930s events,\nand he gave the \"Dizzy From Success\" speech to explain why he was modifying goals of the (20 pts) ",
        "First Five-Year Plan. This leader orchestrated the \"show trials\" of army generals and\nothers, decimating his military before the (10 pts) ",
        "Nazi invasion of his country in Operation\nBarbarossa. For 10 points, name this fan of gulags who was the dictator of the Soviet Union from\n1924 to 1953."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Joseph Stalin",
        "Ioseb Besarionis Dze Jugashvili",
        "Jugashvili"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Theodor Adorno said that after the existence of this place, writing poetry is barbaric.\nThis place was built near a massive, forty-four track (20 pts) ",
        "railway junction and was\ncommanded by Rudolph Hoss. At the main gate of this place, the words \"Arbeit Macht\nFrei\" (pr. ARR-bite mokt FRY), meaning (10 pts) ",
        "\"work makes free,\" were spelled out in iron. It\nwas adjacent to the Birkenau extermination center. For 10 points, name this most active Nazi\ndeath camp, found in Poland."
      ],
      "answer": "Auschwitz"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In an 1890 treaty, this empire abandoned its interest in Zanzibar in exchange for an\noddly shaped territory that granted it access to the Zambezi River, known as the Caprivi\nStrip. This empire perpetrated the Herero genocide in what is now (20 pts) ",
        "Namibia. It had to\ngive up what are now Tanzania and Cameroon following its defeat in (10 pts) ",
        "World War I. For\n10 points, name this European-based empire, which was originally constructed by Otto von\nBismarck."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "German Empire",
        "German"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A succession war named for this area began on the death of Maximilian Joseph in 1777\nand was also known as the \"potato war.\" Motifs from Wagner (pr. VOG-ner) operas are\nused to decorate the (20 pts) ",
        "Neuschwanstein (pr. noy-SHVON-shtine) Castle in this region,\nwhich was built by its (10 pts) ",
        "\"Mad\" king Ludwig II. For 10 points, name this southeastern German\nstate and historic kingdom, where many German Catholics and the city of Munich can be found."
      ],
      "answer": "Bavaria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man coined the name \"scissors crisis\" during the period of the New Economic\nPolicy. He also created the term \"degenerated workers state\" to summarize his views on\nwhat the (20 pts) ",
        "Soviet Union became following his deposition as head of the Red Army. He\nwas ultimately killed in (10 pts) ",
        "Mexico by Ramon Mercador. For 10 points, name this member of\nthe Left Opposition who was outmaneuvered by Joseph Stalin for leadership of the USSR."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Leon Trotsky",
        "Trotsky"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This king was the beneficiary of the original Act of Supremacy. He raised funds for the\nmiddle part of his reign by dissolving nearly all monasteries in his kingdom, with the\nassistance of his first administrator Thomas (20 pts) ",
        "Wolsey. This king was the father of\nEdward VI, (10 pts) ",
        "Mary I, and Elizabeth I. For 10 points, name this king whose attempt to divorce\nCatherine of Aragon triggered the English Reformation and his five subsequent marriages."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry VIII"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this larger operation, soldiers were executed at Chenogne (pr. chay-NON) in\nrevenge for the earlier Malmedy (pr. mahl-may-DEE) Massacre. Anthony McAuliffe issued\nthe singular reply (20 pts) ",
        "\"Nuts!\" to a surrender demand during this operation, which was\nnamed for the (10 pts) ",
        "shape created in a map of troop lines in the Ardennes forest. For 10 points,\nname this late 1944 World War II initiative, the final major German offensive of the war."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Bulge",
        "Bulge"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) A major terrorist group in this country absorbed the Socialist Patients' Collective, a group\nwhich believes that people with illnesses were the oppressed class in capitalist societies, and\nlaunched a 1977 campaign known as its \"autumn.\" This home of the (20 pts) ",
        "Red Army Faction\nwas also where members of (10 pts) ",
        "Black September targeted athletes in 1972. For 10 points, name\nthis country where terrorist incidents included the attack on Israelis at the Munich Olympics."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "West Germany",
        "Germany"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This emperor was the ultimate victor of the Battle of Muhlberg, which suppressed the\nSchmalkaldic (pr. shmal-CALL-dik) League that opposed him. This man's 1525 victory at (20 pts) ",
        "Pavia included the capture of Francis I of France. This father of Philip II summoned (10 pts) ",
        "Martin Luther to the Diet of Worms (pr. VURMZ). For 10 points, name this Hapsburg who\nbriefly united the thrones of Spain and the Holy Roman Empire."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles V",
        "Charles I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This body was originally under the influence of John Pym and the radical \"Five\nMembers,\" and it was convened to raise money following the Bishops' Wars. This body\nsteadily lost members, ending up named sardonically for Nicholas (20 pts) ",
        "Barebones, after its\nmoderate delegates were removed in Pride's Purge to create the (10 pts) ",
        "Rump Parliament. For 10\npoints, name this Parliament which oversaw the English Civil War and is named because it sat\nfrom 1640 to 1660."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Long Parliament",
        "Long"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Guns fired from this building ended the Battle of the Faubourg St. Antoine (pr. foo-BOO\nsont AHN-twan) during the Fronde. This building is where the Marquis de (20 pts) ",
        "Sade enraged\ncrowds by claiming a plot to massacre its inhabitants. Only seven politically unimportant (10 pts) ",
        "prisoners were found inside when it was stormed on July 14, 1789. For 10 points, name this\nParis prison which was destroyed to start the French Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "the Bastille"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's colony fought Susquehannock Indians in the Peach War and granted\nreligious freedom in the Flushing Remonstrance. Prior to England, this country sponsored\nthe original American voyages of Henry (20 pts) ",
        "Hudson. This country conquered the shortlived New Sweden colony in present-day Delaware, under the leadership of Peter (10 pts) ",
        "Stuyvesant. For 10 points, name this country which originally colonized what is now New York."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Netherlands",
        "Holland",
        "the Dutch Empire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This battle turned on the use of a perpendicular two-column approach, and the few losing\nships that escaped were led by Federico Gravina. Prior to this battle, a (20 pts) ",
        "semaphore\nmessage reading \"England expects that every man will do his duty\" was transmitted from\nthe (10 pts) ",
        "Victory. For 10 points, name this 1805 naval battle at which Pierre-Charles Villeneuve\nwas defeated by Horatio Nelson, who died during the fighting and is commemorated at a\nnamesake London square."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Trafalgar",
        "Trafalgar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One leader of this conflict, Jose Sanjurjo, died in a plane crash after leaving Estoril.\nThe term “Fifth Column” was coined during this war. The Abraham Lincoln Brigade was\none of the International Brigades to join this conflict, and (20 pts) ",
        "Nazi Germany supported\none side in this conflict with the Condor Legion. After seizing (10 pts) ",
        "Cartagena, Republican forces\nsurrendered to the Nationalists. For ten points, name this conflict in an Iberian country that brought\nFrancisco Franco to power."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spanish Civil War",
        "Spanish Civil"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man destroyed the Vandals after his generals won the battles of Tricamerum and\nAd Decimum. The Secret History by Procopius detailed the rule of this emperor and his\nmarriage to a (20 pts) ",
        "courtesan who convinced him to stay after a riot by the Blues and\nGreens. This survivor of the Nika Riots formed the (10 pts) ",
        "Corpus Juris Civilis, later known as his\nnamesake “Code.” For ten points, name this Byzantine emperor who built the Hagia Sophia."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Justinian the Great",
        "Justinian I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) The Marquis of Pombal established the Douro Wine Company in this country. A\nsuccession crisis in this country was sparked after the death of (20 pts) ",
        "Sebastian I at the\nBattle of the Three Kings. It gained its independence from its eastern neighbor in the\nRestoration War. The House of (10 pts) ",
        "Braganza ruled, for ten points, what Iberian country\nthat colonized Brazil?"
      ],
      "answer": "Portugal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city’s empire defeated Ercole d’Este to conquer Commachio and defeated a rival in\nthe War of Chioggia. It was targeted by the League of (20 pts) ",
        "Cambrai, founded by its nemesis\nJulius II. Its Arsenale was said to be able to produce one (10 pts) ",
        "warship a day. A fleet from this\ncity was led by Enrico Dandolo in the Fourth Crusade and sacked Constantinople. For ten points, name\nthis “Most Serene Republic” which was ruled by doges."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Most Serene Republic of Venice",
        "Venice"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One man involved in this event used the name John Johnson, and people involved in\nthis event took shelter at the Holbeche House. Francis (20 pts) ",
        "Tresham and Thomas Wintour\nwere executed for their role in this event, and the plan for this event was uncovered in an\nanonymous letter sent to Lord (10 pts) ",
        "Monteagle. Robert Catesby served as the leader behind this\nevent, which saw Guy Fawkes discovered guarding ammunition. For ten points, name this plot to blow up\nthe British Parliament and assassinate James I."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gunpowder Plot",
        "Gunpowder",
        "Treason"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to William of Poitiers, Pope Alexander II gave a papal banner to one leader\nprior to this battle. That leader led an attacking force landed in Pevensey, even though they\nintended to land in the (20 pts) ",
        "Isle of Wight. The other side in this battle had a defensive\nposition on Senlac Hill, where one losing leader was shot in the (10 pts) ",
        "eye. This battle is depicted\non the Bayeux Tapestry, which shows the death of Harold Godwinson. For ten points, name this 1066\nvictory for William the Conqueror, who afterward would establish Norman rule of England."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Hastings",
        "Hastings"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) In response to this event, Mossad launched Operation Wrath of God and\nOperation Spring of Youth. This event’s perpetrators demanded the release of\nAndreas Baader and (20 pts) ",
        "Ulrike Meinhoff, the founders of the Red Army Faction, (10 pts) ",
        "Haganah. For ten points, name this event that saw members of Black September kill 11 Israeli\ncoaches and athletes at the 1972 Summer Olympics in a certain German city."
      ],
      "answer": "Munich Massacre"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Foreigners such as the Scotsman Thomas Gordon were often invited to lead this\norganization. One portion of this organization nearly sparked (20 pts) ",
        "war with Great Britain\nwhile being deployed to relieve another part of this organization, which had been bottled up\nin Port Arthur. That force would proceed to have its T crossed by (10 pts) ",
        "Heihachiro Togo and\nbe destroyed at the Battle of Tsushima Straits. The Baltic and Pacific fleets were part of, for ten points,\nwhat military organization, which experienced a revolt on the battleship Potemkin?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Imperial Russian Navy",
        "Russian Navy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Percy and Charles Neville attempted to overthrow this monarch in the Rising\nof the North. This monarch supported the Dutch in one conflict by signing the Treaty of\nNonsuch, and Francis Walsingham uncovered a plot to assassinate this monarch by Anthony (20 pts) ",
        "Babington, which led to the execution of this monarch’s cousin, Mary Stuart. This\nmonarch spoke of having a “heart and stomach of a (10 pts) ",
        "king” in a speech to troops at Tilbury.\nThe Spanish Armada targeted, for ten points, what “Virgin Queen” of England?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Elizabeth I of England",
        "Elizabeth I",
        "Queen Elizabeth I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group sometimes dressed in women’s clothing as their founder’s “wives,” and\ncarried out their acts using a tool they called “Great Enoch.” This group first appeared in\nNottingham and were threatened with (20 pts) ",
        "capital punishment with the Frame Breaking\nAct. E. J. Hobsbawm referred to their (10 pts) ",
        "sabotage as “collective bargaining by riot.” For ten\npoints, what British textile workers in the early 19th century smashed machines that were replacing their\nlabor and now give their name to those who oppose technological progress?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Luddites"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Duc de Longueville represented the French during the negotiations of this treaty.\nDespite this treaty, Spain and France did not cease hostilities until the Treaty of the (20 pts) ",
        "Pyrenees, and Sweden annexed Bremen after the signature of this treaty. It affirmed the\nindependence of Switzerland and the Netherlands, and it extended the (10 pts) ",
        "Peace of Augsburg\nby allowing Calvinism to be a German state’s official religion. For ten points, name this peace treaty that\nended the Thirty Years War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Peace of Westphalia",
        "Treaty of Westphalia",
        "Westphalia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man founded the newspaper The Spark for his political party. He argued that\ncountries would fight until the rise of socialist governments in the work (20 pts) ",
        "Imperialism,\nthe Highest Stage of Capitalism. He advocated for “state capitalism” in his New Economic\nPolicy as a replacement for “war communism.” In his pamphlet (10 pts) ",
        "“What is to be Done?”\nthis man pushed for the formation of a Vanguard Party to lead the government. For ten points, name this\nSoviet leader who led the Bolsheviks during the October Russian Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Vladimir Lenin",
        "Lenin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This lawyer from Arras was blamed for not stopping the September Massacres. This\nleader of the Montagnards attempted to weaken the movement of de-Christianization by\ncreating the Cult of the (20 pts) ",
        "Supreme Being. He shared power with Lazare Carnot and\nLouis Saint-Just in his highest position, and he executed the (10 pts) ",
        "Girondins and Georges Danton\nbefore being overthrown in the Thermidorian Reaction. For ten points, name this Jacobin who ruled\nduring the “Reign of Terror.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Maximilien Robespierre",
        "Robespierre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After being defeated in World War I, this country lost much of its land in the Treaty of\nTrianon, but some of that land was later restored by Austria in the First Vienna Award.\nThe Nazi-backed (20 pts) ",
        "Arrow Cross Party ended this country’s “regency” after it overthrew\nMiklos (10 pts) ",
        "Horthy. In the aftermath of World War II, this country was occupied by the Soviet Union,\nwhich later put down this country’s 1956 Revolution. For ten points, name this European country with\ncapital Budapest."
      ],
      "answer": "Hungary"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One battle at this site saw Bruno von Mudra and Karl von Eimen lead assaults on\nthe French Fourth army under Henri Gouraud. Another battle here was preceded by the\nreplacement of Charles (20 pts) ",
        "Lanzerac with Louis d’Esprey for “lacking offensive spirit.”\nAfter that battle, Helmuth (10 pts) ",
        "Von Moltke proclaimed “Majesty, we have lost the war” and\nabandoned the Schlieffen plan. Taxicabs brought soldiers to, for ten points, what site of an early Allied\nvictory in WW1 that saved Paris?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Marne River",
        "Marne",
        "Battles of the Marne River"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The fall of this government led to the deportation of many to New Caledonia. Gustave\nCourbet was a member of this government, which ordered the fall of the (20 pts) ",
        "Vendome\nColumn. Many of this government’s officials were executed on the Wall of the Federalists in\nPere Lachaise Cemetery. (10 pts) ",
        "Marshall MacMahon led an army that repressed this government during\nthe “Bloody Week”. For ten points, name this radical socialist government that formed in the French\ncapital in 1871."
      ],
      "answer": "Paris Commune"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hochwald was one of this entity’s over one hundred ouvrages. This entity also included\ndesignated flood zones, but it was not extended to the (20 pts) ",
        "English Channel. It was named\nafter the minister of War who proposed it, and it failed to protect the (10 pts) ",
        "Ardennes forest.\nFor ten points, name this defensive line built by the French to protect against German invasion, which\nfailed when the Nazis avoided it by invading through Belgium instead."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Maginot Line",
        "Maginot"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This event’s capture of Gwailor by forces under Tatya Tose preceded that man’s\nbetrayal at the hands of Man (20 pts) ",
        "Singh. Henry Havelock and Henry Lawrence died\nduring a siege in this event that also saw the Storming of Secundra Bagh and the\nsiege of (10 pts) ",
        "Lucknow. It began after a rumor that the new Enfield Rifles were being lubricated\nwith cow and pig fat. For ten points, name this 1857 Indian rebellion against Great Britiain."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sepoy Mutiny",
        "Sepoy Rebellion",
        "Sepoy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event ended the Peace of Saint-Germain-en-Laye. Pope Gregory XIII sent a Golden\nRose to Charles IX in commemoration of this event, which saw Charles Danowitz kill\nAdmiral (20 pts) ",
        "Gaspard de Coligny. It took place in the aftermath of the marriage between\nMargaret of Valois and (10 pts) ",
        "Henry III of Navarre and was instigated by either Henry of Guise or\nCatherine de Medici. For ten points, name this 1572 massacre of Huguenots."
      ],
      "answer": "St. Bartholowmew’s Day Massacre"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle’s highest ranking English casualty was Edward, Duke of York. The Siege of\nHarfleur preceded this battle, whose losers raided an enemy (20 pts) ",
        "baggage train, causing\nthe winning commander to order prisoner executions. One side in this battle drove sharp\nwooden stakes in front of their position; heavy rain then trapped (10 pts) ",
        "Charles d’Albret’s cavalry\nin deep mud at the mercy of massed English longbows. For ten points, name this 1415 battle of the\nHundred Years War, a victory for Henry V."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Agincourt",
        "Agincourt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Operation Harvest Festival was this event’s largest single action. The Einsatzgruppen\nwere used to carry out this event. At the Wannsee Conference [VAHN-zay Conference],\nit was proposed that (20 pts) ",
        "Scandinavia would not be subject to this event, and ferries to\nSweden thus protected many Danes from it. The Nuremberg (10 pts) ",
        "Trials prosecuted many\nplanners of this event, which was described as the Final Solution. Dachau and Auschwitz were sites of\nconcentration camps during, for ten points, what genocide of Jews and other “undesirables” by Nazi\nGermany during World War II?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Holocaust",
        "Shoah"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader was promoted to Field Marshal after the Battle of Lodz and succeeded\nFriedrich Ebert in his highest post. This man, who named a defensive line set up after the\nBattle of the (20 pts) ",
        "Somme, teamed up with Erich Ludendorff to win the Battle of Tannenberg\nduring World War I. This man was elected President of the (10 pts) ",
        "Weimar Republic in 1925,\nnarrowly defeating Hitler. For ten points, name this German general and statesman who was honored as\nthe namesake of an airship that, in 1937, exploded over New Jersey."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Paul von Hindenburg",
        "Hindenburg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader employed Nikolai Yezhov as the head of a secret police force and approved\nLavrentiy Beria’s plan to kill thousands of dissidents in what is now called the Katyn\nmassacre. This leader may have responded to a rebellion against him by orchestrating a\nmass (20 pts) ",
        "famine in Ukraine, the Holodomor. Hundreds of thousands of political opponents,\nincluding fellow (10 pts) ",
        "Communists, were killed in a Great Purge ordered by this leader from 1936 to\n1938. For ten points, name this dictator of the USSR who ruled during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Joseph Stalin",
        "Stalin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1973, this country’s Prime Minister was assassinated by separatists in Operation\nOgre. Those separatists within this country used (20 pts) ",
        "fueros to protect home rule and\nregional laws until a new constitution was passed in 1812. Luis Carrero Blanco was murdered\nin this country, where King (10 pts) ",
        "Juan Carlos I reigned for four decades. For ten points, name this\nEuropean country where the ETA seeks Basque independence from a country led from Madrid."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Spain",
        "Spain"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler chartered the Levant Company in an attempt to form a trade alliance with\nthe Ottoman Empire. This ruler supported the Netherlands through the Treaty of Nonsuch\nand attacked their enemy at Cadiz with the help of privateer (20 pts) ",
        "Francis Drake. During the\nTilbury speech, this ruler declared that she had the “body of a weak and feeble woman” but\nthe “heart and stomach” of a king while rallying her men against the (10 pts) ",
        "Spanish Armada. For\nten points, name this daughter of Anne Boleyn who succeeded her sister Mary I to become the “Virgin\nQueen” of England."
      ],
      "answer": "Elizabeth I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man suppressed an insurrection by ordering a “whiff of grapeshot” on the 13th\nVendemaire. This man first achieved fame commanding the artillery at the Siege of (20 pts) ",
        "Toulon. This man attempted to reach British possessions in India by invading Egypt, and\nhe returned from exile on the island of (10 pts) ",
        "Elba in his Hundred Days, at the end of which he was\ndefeated by Gebhard von Bl¨ucher and the Duke of Wellington. For ten points, name this French emperor,\nwho was defeated at the Battle of Waterloo."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Napoleon I",
        "Napoleon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man’s 4th Armored Division was able to stop an advance at the Battle of\nMontcornet. He wrote a book on how to modernize his nation’s military titled Army\nof the Future and ousted Henri Giraud for control of a resistance movement. As (20 pts) ",
        "President, this man pulled his nation out of the NATO command structure and\ndeveloped a nuclear weapons program, which carried out tests in (10 pts) ",
        "Algeria. For ten\npoints, name this first president of the Fifth Republic and leader of the Free French during World\nWar II."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles de Gaulle",
        "de Gaulle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This kingdom bought the province of Neumark from the Teutonic Order and attempted\nto establish hegemony with the creation of a customs union called the Zollverein. It\nwas formed after a union of its namesake duchy, now known as (20 pts) ",
        "Kaliningrad, with\nBrandenburg under the Hohenzollern dynasty. This country’s army was reformed by (10 pts) ",
        "Frederick Wilhelm I, making it the most disciplined force in Europe. For ten points, name this kingdom,\nthe largest of the states that founded Germany, with capital at Berlin."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Prussia",
        "Prussia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A monarch of this name commanded troops at the Battle of Dettingen, the last time\na British king did so. Another king of this name was the last British king born outside of\nBritain. Robert (20 pts) ",
        "Walpole, the first prime minister of Great Britain, served under a\nmonarch of this name. A ruler with this name came to power after the abdication of (10 pts) ",
        "Edward VIII and was the father of Queen Elizabeth. For ten points, give this name of six British kings,\nthe third of which opposed American independence."
      ],
      "answer": "George"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country converted to Protestantism after the Count’s Feud, and it started the\nScanian War with its northern neighbor. It signed the Treaty of (20 pts) ",
        "Kiel during the\nNapoleonic Wars, forcing it to grant independence to one of its territories, and its king\nValdemar IV conquered Gotland. Prussia and Austria forced this country to cede the Duchy\nof (10 pts) ",
        "Schleswig-Holstein, and it fought the Victual Brothers over their piracy in the Baltic. It joined in\nthe Kalmar Union with two of its neighbors, Norway and Sweden. For ten points, name this country that\nhas endured several sieges of Copenhagen."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Denmark",
        "Denmark"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country antagonized a neighbor via the Hallstein Doctrine, a brief policy of breaking\ndiplomatic relations with countries that officially recognized that neighbor. Foreign agents\nwithin this country sponsored the far-left (20 pts) ",
        "Red Army Faction, which was co-founded by\nAndreas Baader. This country tried to improve relations with its neighbor via ostpolitik, as\nsupported by (10 pts) ",
        "Willy Brandt. This country was divided into British, American, and French zones via\nan agreement at the Yalta conference. For ten points, name this European country that, in 1990, re-united\nwith its eastern neighbor."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "West Germany",
        "Federal Republic of Germany",
        "FRG"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This general went around the Gazala Line to defeat Claude Auchinleck and stopped\nOperation Battleaxe. He commanded Army Group B in defense of Northern Italy and\ndesigned the Atlantic (20 pts) ",
        "Wall. A tank division he commanded was nicknamed the “Ghost”\nDivision for moving to fast to be tracked. He launched several offensives aimed at (10 pts) ",
        "Cairo,\nbut was defeated by Bernard Montgomery at the Battle of El Alamein. For ten points, name this Nazi\nGerman commander of the North African campaign, nicknamed the “Desert Fox.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Erwin Rommel",
        "Rommel"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The name of a river in this modern-day country now means “disaster” in French after\nan 1812 victory for Peter Wittgenstein. A World War II battle fought in this country ended\nwith the creation of the Navahrudak pocket. Napoleon’s forces were harried across the\nBerezina River in this country. Negotiations held in this modern country gave the (20 pts) ",
        "Baltic States to Germany; Leon Trotsky agreed to those concessions in the Treaty of (10 pts) ",
        "Brest-Litovsk. For ten points, name this country led by Alexander Lukashenko from its capital at Minsk."
      ],
      "answer": "Belarus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This movement began in Arnold due to hosiery falling out of fashion. The Pentrich riots\nwere started by Jeremiah Brandreth, a former member of this movement. Members of this\nmovement executed William Horsfall and attacked Rawfolds (20 pts) ",
        "Mill. The Swing Riots\nwas an agricultural version of this movement, which was suppressed by the 1812 Frame\nBreaking Act. A man named Ned who legendarily smashed two (10 pts) ",
        "knitting frames inspired,\nfor ten points, what anti-Industrial Revolution movement in England that opposed new technologies?"
      ],
      "answer": "Luddites"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group bombed the fishing boat of Lord Mountbatten and pushed for the “five\ndemands” during a hunger strike led by Bobby Sands. In 1984, it planted a bomb in the\nGrand Hotel in (20 pts) ",
        "Brighton in a failed assassination attempt on Margaret Thatcher,\nbut it agreed to a cease fire in 1997 after its affiliated political party was allowed into the\nnegotiations for the (10 pts) ",
        "Good Friday agreement. Sinn F´ein was associated with, for ten points, what\nparamilitary group at the forefront of “the Troubles” that fought for an independent Ireland?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Provisional Irish Republican Army",
        "PIRA",
        "IRA",
        "Irish Republican Army"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Louis XII was invited by Venice to conquer this city, although he was eventually forced\nout after the battles of Ravenna and Novara. This city contains the only Gothic cathedral in\nItaly. After the death of (20 pts) ",
        "Filip Maria Visconti, this city briefly experienced the Golden\nAmbrosian Republic. This city led a league that opposed Emperor Frederick II and won the\nBattle of (10 pts) ",
        "Legnano, and it was ruled in the Renaissance by Francesco, Ludovico, and other members\nof the Sforza family. For ten points, name this northern Italian city, the historic capital of Lombardy."
      ],
      "answer": "Milan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man’s attempt to avoid conflict was documented in a telegram to “cousin\nWilly.” Father Gapon’s insurrection took place during the reign of this ruler, who was\npersuaded to sign the (20 pts) ",
        "October manifesto after angering the populace on Bloody\nSunday. In the mid-20th century, numerous imposters claimed to be this man’s (10 pts) ",
        "daughter, Anastasia, who was killed with the rest of this man’s family by the Bolsheviks in 1918.\nFor ten points, name this final Romanov Tsar of Russia."
      ],
      "answer": "Nicholas II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Early in this monarch’s reign, the Earl of Bute was employed as prime minister. Newgate\nPrison burned down during the reign of this monarch, who also faced the Gordon Riots.\nGeorge Grenville worked under this monarch, who barred expansion west of the (20 pts) ",
        "Appalachians. Lord North passed the Townshend Acts and the (10 pts) ",
        "Intolerable Acts while\nserving, for ten points, what English king who rejected the Olive Branch Petition.and lost control over\nthe colonies in the American Revolution?"
      ],
      "answer": "George III"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This government’s attempt to unify Protestantism was opposed by Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s\nConfessing Church. The Red Orchestra and White Rose groups opposed this government,\nwhich attacked modernist art at the (20 pts) ",
        "Degenerate Art Exhibition. Leni Riefenstahl’s film\nTriumph of the Will was produced with the help of Joseph (10 pts) ",
        "Goebbels, this government’s\npropaganda minister. For ten points, name this regime that created the Nuremberg Laws to persecute\nJews before engineering the Holocaust."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nazi Germany",
        "Nazi",
        "Germany",
        "National Socialist German Workers’ Party",
        "NSGWP",
        "the Third Reich"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) In case of one war, this country planned to rush through its northern neighbor\nto the Dyle River. This country’s navy was attacked by its own ally at Mers-el-K´ebir\nand forced to scuttle its own ships at (20 pts) ",
        "Toulon. This country built a defensive\nstructure called the Maginot Line that was bypassed by a (10 pts) ",
        "blitzkrieg through the\nArdennes forest. For ten points, name this country that was split into German-occupied north and\nVichy south after its defeat in World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler began to implement reforms after a series of violent uprisings in Tambov\nand Kronstadt. To follow up on a prior promise of “peace, land, and bread,” this ruler was\nforced to adopt the free market New (20 pts) ",
        "Economic Policy. This ruler consolidated power\nafter defeating the White (10 pts) ",
        "Menshevik, faction in a civil war. Though he designated Leon Trotsky\nas his successor, this man was ultimately replaced by Joseph Stalin. For ten points, name this first leader\nof the Soviet Union."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Vladimir Lenin",
        "Lenin",
        "Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov",
        "Ulyanov"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This city formed a treaty of alliance with Jerusalem in the Pactum Warmundi.\nPope Julius II tried to subdue this city by allying with France and the Holy Roman\nEmpire in the League of (20 pts) ",
        "Cambrai. Zara and Constantinople were sacked by\nsoldiers during the Fourth Crusade in exchange for ships from this city’s ruler, (10 pts) ",
        "Enrico Dandolo. Doges [doh-zhes] ruled, for ten points, what Italian city-state, a rival of Genoa\nknown for its empire on the Adriatic and its system of canals?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Most Serene Republic of Venice",
        "Venice"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1572 in this city, a man known as “Besme” [BEHM] stabbed an admiral and threw\nhim out a window, where he was then decapitated. Shortly after Margaret of Valois was\nmarried in this city, a massacre of (20 pts) ",
        "Huguenots took place on Saint Bartholomew’s Day.\nIn converting to Catholicism, Henry IV claimed that this city was (10 pts) ",
        "“well worth a mass.”\nFor ten points, name this capital city, the site of much strife during the French Wars of Religion."
      ],
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the Reformation, this country underwent two civil wars called the Wars of\nKappel. The last Duke of Burgundy, Charles the Bold, died while fighting this country. The\nthree (20 pts) ",
        "cantons of Uri, Schwyz, and Unterwalden joined to form this country in the\nFederal Charter of 1291. This country was the site of renowned mercenaries, including the\nbodyguard of the (10 pts) ",
        "Pope, and hosted John Calvin in the city of Geneva. For ten points, name this\nAlpine confederacy governed from Bern that is traditionally neutral in European wars."
      ],
      "answer": "Switzerland"
    }
  ]
}